










                                                           April 16, 2013


               Honorable Mayor and City Council
               City of Norfolk, Virginia

               I respectfully submit to you the Proposed Fiscal Year 2014 financial plan for the City of Norfolk,
               which is comprised of the Operating, Internal Service Fund, Enterprise Fund, Special Revenue
               Fund, Capital Budget, and Annual Plan for the Housing and Urban Development Block Grant
               programs.  A summary of the Proposed Financial Plan is shown in the table below.


                                            Fiscal Year (FY) 2014 Financial Plan

                              Fund                                         Proposed Budget
                              General Fund                                     $811,504,726

                              Enterprise Funds                                 $130,992,500

                              Special Revenue Funds                             $60,875,771

                              Internal Service Fund                             $13,655,900
                              Total Operating Funds                          $1,017,028,897

                              Healthcare Fund                                   $57,931,973

                              Total Operating with Healthcare Fund           $1,074,960,870
                              Capital Improvement Plan                         $127,290,582

                              Total Operating and Capital Funds              $1,202,251,452

                              Annual Plan for HUD Block Grants                   $5,678,928

                              Total Financial Plan                           $1,207,930,380

               The Proposed General Fund budget is $811.5 million.  The total General Fund budget increase is
               $11.7 million or a 1.5 percent increase from the Approved FY 2013 Budget.  As in recent years,
               the Proposed FY 2014 Budget continues efforts to streamline government and contain costs as
               we find our footing during this time of economic uncertainty.  Therefore, the budget I present
               to you today does not contain “bells and whistles” but mainly provides the resources needed to
               continue services as we know them today.

               During the last three years, the city has made difficult but necessary decisions through the
               economic downturn.  However, as we enter another year of tough economic times, the





 = Page 1 =








               avenues available to minimize revenue loss are becoming scarce.  It will be increasingly difficult
               to  find  savings  in  the  future  since  we  have  already  reviewed  existing  operations  and
               implemented efficiencies, reduced current programs, deferred projects, and delayed necessary
               infrastructure repairs that may increase costs in the future.   We are committed to streamlining
               government and employing best practices, but our current needs and service levels exceed our
               available resources.

               While I am presenting to you a balanced budget, it should not be mistaken for a    structurally
               balanced  budget. A  structurally balanced  budget matches ongoing expenditures with ongoing
               revenues.  The Proposed FY 2014 Budget development process included making tough choices
               and used one-time revenues for ongoing expenses to preserve our current level of service.
               Additionally, the Proposed Budget maintains service levels that were decided on last year,
               which included restorations that opened libraries on Mondays and expanded pool hours at
               recreation centers.

               With the various tradeoffs made during the budget development process, the Proposed FY
               2014 Budget continues our goal of being a well-managed government and is highlighted by the
               following:

                       Provides a two percent salary increase for city employees effective January 2014
                       Increases the Real Estate Tax Rate by two cents from $1.11 to $1.13  and dedicates  all
                       revenues   from  the  increase  to  the  new  School  Construction,  Technology,  and
                       Infrastructure (CTI) Program
                       Provides a strategy to fully fund Norfolk Public Schools (NPS) FY 2014 budget request
                       Continues to realign, reallocate, and refocus resources in support of the six priority
                       areas with an emphasis on two priorities; Lifelong Learning, and Economic Vitality and
                       Workforce Development
                       Accelerates the design and construction of two fire stations
                       Implements a city-administered healthcare plan resulting is significant savings for the
                       city, NPS, and Norfolk Redevelopment and House Authority
                       Decentralizes central Storehouse operations
                       Consolidates Communications and Public Information with Information Technology to
                       form the new Department of Communications and Technology, reducing operating
                       redundancies
                       Continues IMPACT to improve customer service
                       Continues implementation of “Smart Processing” and increases Planning fees to support

                       needed technology improvements
                       Increases Ambulance fees to support the cost increase for     time critical emergency
                       response and effective patient care
                       Increases  Police  Record  Service  Fees  for   Fingerprinting,  Accident  Reports,  Incident
                       Reports and Criminal Records to help offset the expenses associated with providing
                       these services.


                                                                                                      2



 = Page 2 =









               GUIDING PRINCIPLES
               The Proposed FY 2014 Operating and Capital Improvement Budgets continue efforts launched
               in  February  2011  to  become  a  well-managed  government.    Throughout  the  budget
               development process, the following principles have been employed to achieve results: we
               reinvested existing resources to fund the city’s highest priorities; engaged employees and
               residents in the budget development process; identified further opportunities for operating
               efficiencies through internal and external collaboration; eliminated redundant processes and
               trimmed  excess  from  the  budget;  increased  employee  productivity  throughout  the
               organization; and continued to focus on cost containment measures.  These principles continue
               to support the efforts undertaken by City Council over the past three years.

               Uneven economic recovery, stagnant revenue collections, and rising costs of providing services
               have required us to focus on additional cost containment strategies to maintain the level of
               service Council approved in FY 2013.  These additional strategies are needed to address cost
               increases that are outside of our control, such as state and federal mandates, inflation, and
               rising energy and utility costs.  The changing healthcare landscape, the increasing cost of
               retirement and debt service, and the opening of new facilities are challenges we will continue
               to face in the future.

               These guiding principles outlined above will continue throughout FY 2014 to increase overall
               performance.  However, as we continue to examine opportunities to reduce costs, we must
                                                       y
               also move towards building a  structurall  balanced  budget to secure and improve the financial
               position of the city.

               BUDGETING BASED ON PRIORITIES
               As you may recall, together we undertook a priority setting process.  The Proposed FY 2014
               Budget is built around those six City Council priorities:

                       Accessibility, Mobility and Connectivity
                       Economic Vitality and Workforce Development
                       Environmental Sustainability
                       Lifelong Learning
                       Safe, Healthy and Inclusive Communities
                       Well-Managed Government

               While work continues on all six priorities, this year’s Proposed Budget focuses on two priority
               areas;   Lifelong  Learning      Economic  Vitality  and  Workforce  Development   .    All  city
                                         , and
               departments were instructed during this year’s budget development process to focus on these
               two priorities.





                                                                                                      3



 = Page 3 =








               FINANCIAL BACKDROP
               Although the ‘Great Recession’ officially ended in June 2009, the recovery has been uneven
               across sectors of the economy.  State governments, which rely on income and sales taxes, have
               improved with the growth in jobs and recovery of consumer spending.  Local governments,
               which are heavily reliant on property taxes, have lagged and been held back by the slow
               recovery of the housing market.  The recent uptick in the regional and local housing markets is
               encouraging.  In Norfolk, the median and average sales price of homes sold in 2012 rose by 5.1
               percent, the first annual increase since 2007.  However, distressed homes, which are typically
               sold at a discount, continue to make up a significant portion of homes for sale in the region.
               While the housing market is beginning to stabilize, the recovery is still slow and inconsistent.

                                                      Jobs  in  the  region  continued  to  grow  in  2012  but
                                                      remained below pre-recession levels.    Additionally, the
                                                      recovery  may  be  set  back  by  the  impact  of
                                                      Sequestration.  According to Moody’s Investors Service
                                                      (Moody’s), Virginia is at the top of the list of states
                                                      expected to be impacted by Sequestration due to the
                                                      high concentration of defense procurement spending in
                                                      the state.  Consequently, Moody’s assigned Virginia a
                                                      negative outlook.  Since defense spending makes up
               nearly 46 percent of our regional economy, Hampton Roads and Norfolk are likely to be
               impacted by Sequestration.

               While the impacts are unknown at this time, Sequestration could directly impact Norfolk
               through the loss of funding from various federal programs such as the Department of Housing
               and Urban Developments’ Community Development Block Grant Program, the Department of
               Education’s Impact Aid, and the Department of Labor’s Workforce Investment Act state grants.

               STRUCTURAL BALANCE
               What does it mean to have a structurally balanced budget?  Simply said, structural balance
               exists when ongoing expenses are tied to recurring revenue sources.  When I arrived in Norfolk
               in 2004, the budget document that year outlined issues relating to the structural imbalance of
               $26 million between revenues and expenditures.  Many of the issues that led to the imbalance
               then are the same ones we face today including: a slowdown of national economic recovery;
               the continued escalation for the cost of goods and services; increased cost of healthcare and
               the city’s retirement system; the continued reduction of state funding to the city; and the
               accumulation of previously deferred maintenance and replacement of critical infrastructure.

               A structurally balanced budget is one mechanism to combat the cyclical effects of these types
               of financial issues.  Additionally, the factors that support a structurally balanced budget are
               used in determining the fiscal health of the city and credit rating agencies use it to grade
               Norfolk in the bond market.  We believe structural balance can be achieved within the next five
               years.  To do this, we need to implement a combination of revenue and expenditure actions.

                                                                                                      4



 = Page 4 =








               We must be practical in our spending, make ongoing and sustainable reductions, and find new
               cost efficient ways of providing services.  Additionally, we must have greater flexibility in raising
               revenue.

               As part of our effort to be a well-managed government, the establishment and maintenance of
               general operating reserves is considered one of the most effective management practices a
               local government can employ.  Reserves help to cushion against annual cash flow disruptions.
               Specifically  during  FY  2012,  we  allocated  $773,328  of  the  FY  2011  surplus  to  raise  the
               unassigned General Fund balance to $42 million to further strengthen reserves.  As a result, the
               unassigned General Fund balance currently exceeds five percent of the budget with the
               aspiration to increase this goal over the next decade.    Additionally, the city has increased the
               Risk Management as well as the Economic Downturn/Leveling Reserves.  The Risk Management
               Reserve was enhanced in FY 2010 and FY 2012 to $3 million and we allocated $1 million of the
               FY 2011 surplus to the Economic Downturn/Leveling Reserve, for a total of $3 million.

               The decline in revenue from major revenue sources since the start of the Great Recession
               resulted in the city increasing its reliance on carryforward funds to balance the budget.  As real
               estate assessments declined, the use of carryforward funds increased significantly in FY 2012
               and FY 2013, accounting for at least two percent ($16-$19 million) of the Approved Budget.
               Without the carryforward, the budget would have needed to remain flat even though the city
               still faced rising operating costs.

               The carryforwards and actions to realign, reallocate, and refocus resources enabled the city to
               provide a balanced budget in FY 2013.  This balanced budget was accomplished without raising
               taxes or reducing service levels, and with minimal reductions in staff.  However, the ability to
               maintain service levels without a full recovery in real estate valuations is not sustainable.

               WHAT HAS BEEN DONE TO ADDRESS THE IMBALANCE?
               Throughout FY 2013, we worked to forge partnerships that would leverage existing resources to
               increase efficiencies.  One of the major initiatives undertaken in FY 2013 regarding shared
               services involved the Hampton Roads Partnership and their efforts to bring the cities of Norfolk,
               Chesapeake, and Virginia Beach together to identify at least 13
               service sharing opportunities across jurisdictional lines.  The first
               three of these initiatives are:
                       Sign  Shop  Services  -  Manufacturing  of  standard  traffic
                       control  signs  for  the  three  cities  that  will  save  Norfolk
                       approximately  $15,000  per  year,  as  well  as  increase
                       efficiency of sign installation and repair services through an
                       agreement signed between the three cities.  Virginia Beach
                       has taken the lead to oversee sign production.

                       Elevator Inspections - Norfolk is reviewing Chesapeake’s processes for contracting out
                       elevator inspections.  The new model could result in the cities sharing third party

                                                                                                      5



 = Page 5 =








                       inspectors for the inspection of elevators in public and private buildings.
                       Permitting Services - The three cities are working collaboratively on standardizing
                       permitting processes beginning with the use of common forms for various building
                       permit applications.  A long-range goal is to provide the public access to an online
                       permitting process through a shared internet portal.

               Sharing services also encourages work across traditional organizational structures by removing
               silos to create operating efficiencies. Additionally, the benefits of these types of agreements

               have led the city to move forward with: developing a joint grass cutting initiative on public
               property with Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority (NRHA); internally decentralizing
               its  central  Storehouse  operations;  and  working  to  strengthen  the  Norfolk  Healthcare
               Consortium.  The joint grass cutting initiative with NRHA will promote citywide beautification
               efforts, improve efficiencies by reducing mobilization costs and allow for the clustering of
               properties for grass cutting in specific areas of the city.  Some of these initiatives are further
               detailed under the “Efficiency and Effectiveness” section of this message.


               HOW HAVE NEIGHBORING LOCALITIES ADDRESSED BUDGET IMBALANCES?
               The city’s path to a balanced budget in the period of declining revenues has been markedly
               different than the path chosen by most of our neighbors. The cities of Portsmouth, Suffolk, and
               Virginia Beach have addressed their budget imbalance by raising taxes.  Since FY 2010, these
               three cities have increased their real estate tax rate as identified in the following chart.






































                                                                                                      6



 = Page 6 =








               Our continued dependence on carryforwards and the desire to maintain the current service
               levels in the long-term requires the city, like other Hampton Roads communities, to increase
               revenues by way of real estate tax increases.    While it has been three years since the first
               Hampton Roads city began increasing real estate taxes, we have maintained the same tax rate
               as prior to the recession; however, the increasing fiscal stress presents challenges in our
               available options.

               FISCAL STRESS
               Norfolk is identified in the Commission on Local Government’s most recent report as the 11   th
               most fiscally stressed community out of 134 localities in the Commonwealth.  The fiscal stress
               index is a measure of a locality’s overall fiscal well being relative to other localities in Virginia.
               The fiscal stress index is comprised of three components:

                       Revenue capacity per capita (the potential ability of a locality to raise revenue)

                       Revenue effort (the extent to which a locality has used its revenue capacity)

                       Median household income

               The chart below provides a comparison of Norfolk’s fiscal stress index in relation to other
               localities across the state.


                                                                                                  Low
                                                                                                 Stress
                 High                Above Average Stress                 Below Average
                 Stress                                                       Stress











              Norfolk rank:
                   11





             Covington  Petersburg  Franklin City  Buena Vista  Bristol  Norfolk  Hopewell  Norton  Roanoke City  Richmond City  Dickenson  Sussex  Bedford  Smyth  Cumberland  Alleghany  Greensville  Lee  Tazewell  Colonial Heights  Pulaski  Prince Edward  Lunenburg  Charlotte  Nottoway  Halifax  Wythe  Fredericksburg  Bland  Montgomery  Pittsylvania  Williamsburg  Richmond Co.  Prince George  Washington  Accomack  Appomattox  Roanoke County  Caroline  Chesapeake  Amelia  Charles City  Essex  Wa



                Not all localities are shown due to size limitation.





                                                                                                      7



 = Page 7 =








               REVENUE PICTURE
               Real estate tax revenue is the largest locally-generated revenue source and makes up a quarter
               of the city’s General Fund revenue.  In the past three years, real estate assessments have
               declined and as a result, the city has lost an estimated $15 million in real estate tax revenue.
               This is no small loss.  Assessments would have had to grow by about eight percent (or an
               increase of nine cents on the tax rate) to get back to the same level as FY 2010.

               In FY 2014, overall real estate assessments are projected to increase by approximately 0.11
               percent based on a preliminary estimate from the Real Estate Assessor’s Office.  However, this
               increase does not apply to all homeowners.  Residential assessments (including condominiums)
               are projected to decline again for the fourth consecutive year in FY 2014, by about one percent.
               This means that of the 272 neighborhoods, only 66 neighborhoods, or one in four, will see an
               increase in assessed value.

































               The last time the city raised the real estate tax rate was in FY 1996, when the tax rate went
               from $1.38 to $1.40.  Since that time, as real estate assessments soared from 2003 to its peak in
               2010, the city reduced the tax rate by 29 cents over a three year period, from $1.40 to $1.11.
               The Proposed Budget includes a two-cent increase in the real estate tax rate from $1.11 to
               $1.13. The revenue from the tax increase will be dedicated entirely to NPS to create the
               Construction, Technology, and Infrastructure (CTI) program.  The CTI is further detailed under
               the “Lifelong Learning” section of this message.

               If residential assessments did not change from last year, a two-cent increase would have cost
               the  average  homeowner  about  $40  per  year.    But  because  of  the  projected  decline  in
               residential assessments in FY 2014, the average homeowner’s tax bill will only increase by


                                                                                                      8



 = Page 8 =








               about  $13,  from  $2,258  to  $2,271  with  the  two-cent  increase.    Moreover,  the  average
               homeowner, with the two-cent increase, will still be paying about $304 less than they were in
               FY 2010, when residential assessments were at their peak.  The average homeowner in one in
               five neighborhoods will see no increase in their tax bill.

                             Impact of FY 2014 Proposed 2¢ Increase in the Real Estate Tax Rate

                       FY 2013:  Average homeowner’s tax bill (at  $1.11 rate )                $2,258
                       Increase in average homeowner’s bill if rate increases by 2¢               $40

                       FY 2014:  Average homeowner’s tax bill (at  $1.11 rate )                $2,230
                       Average savings from decline in residential assessments                   -$27

                       FY 2014 Proposed:  Average homeowner’s tax bill (at  $1.13 rate, 2¢ increase )   $2,271
                       Difference from average homeowner’s tax bill in FY 2013                    $13

                       Difference from average homeowner’s tax bill in FY 2010 of $2,575        -$304

                       Note: Amounts may not sum due to rounding.

               Aside from real estate, other local taxes are projected to hold steady.  However, these revenues
               are sensitive to changes in economic activity.  The uncertainty of Sequestration and the end of
               the payroll tax holiday may negatively impact this revenue.    These revenue sources make up
               about 19 percent of General Fund revenue and include various taxes such as, sales, business
               license, hotel and motel, restaurant, and recordation taxes.  Overall, these local taxes began to
               rise in FY 2011 after declining for two straight years and have been gradually approaching pre-
               recession levels.

               Revenues from the Commonwealth are expected to increase by about $2.6 million to nearly
               $292 million in FY 2014.  This projected increase is largely due to the restoration of the flexible
               reduction in aid to localities, which was first imposed in the FY 2009 budget.  However, state
               revenues  are  still  below  pre-recession  levels  and  not  all  the  reductions  from  the
               Commonwealth have been restored.  Five years ago, revenues from the Commonwealth made
               up about 41 percent of the FY 2009 General Fund budget; in FY 2014, these sources make up 36
               percent of General Fund budget, a loss of $46 million.

               USER FEE INCREASES
               In addition to the proposed two-cent increase to the real
               property tax rate, I am proposing user fee increases in four
               areas in response to the rising costs to provide services.
               User fee increases are proposed for various Norfolk-Fire
               Ambulance fees, Police Record fees, Planning fees, and
               Parking  fees.    The  increasing  cost  of  delivering  these
               services has resulted in a proposed fee increase to recoup
               a greater percent of the actual cost for services provided.

                                                                                                      9



 = Page 9 =








               User  fee  increases  are  proposed  for  Norfolk’s  Fire-Rescue  fees  for  ambulance  services.
               Periodically, the city reviews the rate structure with its emergency medical services billing
               provider to ensure that the city is achieving the maximum insurance funding for these services.
               Based on the most recent review, it is recommended that the city increase these rates.

                                 Police Record Service Fee increases are also proposed for     Fingerprinting,
                                 Accident Reports, Incident Reports and Criminal Records to help offset the
                                 expenses associated with providing them.  After researching the user fees of
                                 other cities, it has been determined the City of Norfolk’s user fees are
                                 relatively low in comparison and do not cover the cost of production.  The
                                 Police Record Service fees will be increased to $10.00 to help offset the
                                 expenses associated with providing them.  The change in fee structure for
                                 record services is projected to increase revenue by almost $100,000 per year.

               Planning user fee increases are proposed to be reinvested back into our “Smart Processing”
               initiatives  for  technology  improvements.    Smart  Processing  is  a  philosophy  promoting
               exceptional customer service by ensuring businesses and
               homeowners  have  a  seamless  experience  while  going
               through the city’s development process.

               The  city’s  Parking  System,  which  consists  of  more  than
               20,400 spaces, including 15 garages, nine lots and over 700 parking meters, has been a
               cornerstone for Downtown revitalization and economic vitality over the last 15 years.  The
               Parking System’s expenses are covered solely through the user fees of the self-supporting
               Parking Enterprise Fund.  User fee rate adjustments, which were last implemented in 2009,
               have not kept pace with inflation, while expenses continue to escalate.  To maintain fiscal
               stability, the Proposed Budget recommends several financial and operational changes, including
               some user fee rate adjustments.  The proposal:

                           Increases transient or short-term parking rates, except at
                          MacArthur Center
                           Increases parking meter rates in Downtown and around Old

                          Dominion University
                           Increases fines for parking violations
                           Expands automation in the parking garages
                           Institutes annual rate adjustments beginning in 2017 for transient, meter, and
                          violation prices that are tied to the rate of inflation

               It should be noted that the expansion of automation in parking garages is a parking industry
               best  practice.    This  practice  optimizes  operations  through  the  use  of  technology.    It  is
               anticipated that fully automated lanes will go into effect at the beginning of calendar year 2014.




                                                                                                    10



 = Page 10 =








               There are no user fee rate adjustments proposed for monthly parking, which also includes
               residential parkers.  Additionally, no proposed user fee rate adjustment is recommended for
               recreational rates.

               EXPENDITURE CHALLENGES – OPERATING BUDGET
               Revenue losses over the last three years have significantly impacted the city’s ability to operate
               at identified service levels.  Operating costs are significantly impacted in the Proposed FY 2014
               Budget  by  healthcare,  retirement,  inflation,  and  increases  in  energy.    To  address  the
               expenditure challenges, it was our goal throughout the budget development process to begin
               the groundwork for a more structurally balanced budget in order to further strengthen the
               city’s fiscal health.  However, at this point in time, to meet existing expenditure challenges and
               to minimize layoffs, the city’s reliance on carryforwards to support operations will continue.

































               A major cost driver in the Proposed Budget is the city’s contribution to the Norfolk Employees
               Retirement System (NERS).  Two actions in FY 2013 have had significant impacts on the
               Proposed Budget.  Last year, the Approved FY 2013 Budget provided a two percent cost of living
               adjustment (COLA) for retirees.  This COLA increased annual retirement payout costs by
               approximately $1.4 million.  While we would like to provide our retirees a COLA it is not
               factored into the base calculations. The Retirement Board has indicated that should we provide
               COLAs regularly it would become a standard practice versus an ad hoc one.  Once it becomes a
               standard practice, it will have a significant impact on the city’s contribution formula for
               retirement.  A second action impacting retirement costs was the transition of the Norfolk
               Community Services Board (NCSB) into the city’s structure.  Bringing NCSB employees into the
               city’s retirement system also contributed to the increase of the FY 2014 retirement costs.



                                                                                                    11



 = Page 11 =








               Similar to retirement costs, healthcare costs are a significant component of the budget.  The
               city is a member of the Norfolk Healthcare Consortium (Consortium), along with NPS and the
               NRHA. The Consortium has worked to employ best practices to keep costs below the national
               and regional average.  Even with these efforts, healthcare premiums have increased 6.4 and 7.7
               percent over the last two plan years respectively.  In December, the Consortium’s healthcare
               consultant projected a 15.2 percent premium increase beginning in January 2014.

               The increase is due to both an annual healthcare cost increase assumption, and the beginning
               of the Affordable Care Act in 2014.  To control costs and limit the impact on the city and our
               employees,  the  Proposed  FY  2014  Budget  includes  the  transition  to  a  city-administered
               healthcare  model effective  January  2014.    The  proposed  model  is  similar  to  what  most
               Hampton Roads cities currently use.  The transition, which is projected to save the city and our
               employees $2.5 million in FY 2014, is further detailed under the “Efficiency and Effectiveness”
               section of this message.

               Even with the significant challenges facing the city, there are opportunities to proactively
               develop strategies in the short and long-term to improve the city’s financial position.  Short-
               term strategies include:
                       Re-evaluate the effectiveness of programs and services that receive General Fund
                       subsidies;
                       Strengthen  Internal  Service  Funds  and  Enterprise  Funds  to  ensure  they  are  self-
                       supporting; and
                       Engage citizens in conversations about the expected levels of services and what we can
                       really afford to fund.

               Long-term strategies include:
                       Reduce the use of one-time revenues to fund ongoing operating costs for a more
                       structurally balanced budget;
                       Reduce the use of year-end budget surpluses to fund ongoing operations;
                       Temper the use of bond financing and decrease the city’s debt burden; and
                       Increase the reserves to help address shortfalls and potential costs of catastrophic
                       events.

               EFFICIENCY AND EFFECTIVENESS
               During the economic downturn, the city began new efficiency initiatives to continue providing
               quality  programs  and  services  to  Norfolk’s  residents,  businesses,  and  visitors.    Strategic
               realignment, benchmarking performance measurement, budgeting to priorities, and service
               sharing agreements are now integrated into city operations as part of being a well-managed
               government.

               During the FY 2013 budget development process, the city identified strategic initiatives that
               would enhance operating efficiencies.  After last year’s budget was approved, we continued our
               efforts to:

                                                                                                    12



 = Page 12 =









                       Collaborate with adjacent cities to create shared services agreements
                       Create partnerships with NRHA and NPS to make government operations more efficient
                       Closeout accounts that have had no activity for a specified time period
                       Re-evaluate aspects of how we manage our debt to better utilize funds and ensure the
                       lowest possible borrowing costs are achieved
                       Consolidate departments and services for greater operating efficiencies

               The recession has also resulted in all city departments re-evaluating their operations.  We are
               identifying opportunities for operational efficiencies that not only improve productivity but
               focus on cost containment.  In FY 2014, the city will continue efforts to drive down the cost of
               doing business.  Actions proposed include:

                       Decentralize central Storehouse operations
                       Move the city’s Real Estate Division from the Department of General Services to the
                       Department of Development
                       Move the city’s Purchasing Office from the Department of General Services to the
                       Department of Finance
                       Consolidate  the  Department  of  Information  Technology  with  the  Office  of
                       Communications  and  Public  Information  to  form  the  new  Department  of
                       Communications and Technology

               Beginning in FY 2014, the central Storehouse will be decentralized and purchases will be
               procured and monitored by individual departments.  The decentralization of the Storehouse is
               considered an industry-wide best practice that will improve operating efficiencies by promoting
               just-in-time delivery of goods purchased and reducing the costs associated with maintaining
               inventories in-house.

                                In addition to the strategic realignment and reprogramming of resources, the
                                city is exploring ways to combat the rising cost of healthcare.  The Consortium,
                                as stated earlier, is focused on providing affordable healthcare for Consortium
                                members.  Since its inception, the Consortium has used plan design changes,
                                wellness programs, and most recently, a dependent care audit to stabilize the
                                growth of healthcare costs.  The Consortium, as part of the Proposed FY 2014
                                Budget, will transition to city-administered health insurance beginning January
                                2014 from a fully insured model.  Under the new model, the Consortium will
               assume the risk and responsibility for the administration and payment of claims rather than
               paying a private insurance company to assume the risk. A self-insured model allows the
               Consortium to fully control all aspects of the plan, including setting rates to smooth out the
               impact of increases on employees.  The city-administered healthcare program will be similar to
               how we already handle risk management.



                                                                                                    13



 = Page 13 =








               To do this, the Proposed FY 2014 Budget includes the creation of a Healthcare Fund.  The fund
               will receive revenue from employee, employer, and participating retiree healthcare premiums
               for all Consortium agencies.  These funds will be used to pay medical claims, administrative
               costs, wellness program costs, and fees related to the Affordable Care Act.  Any revenue earned
               in excess of expenditures will be held as a premium stabilization reserve to mitigate premium
               increases in future years.

               The transition to a city-administered plan is projected to save the city an estimated $2 million,
               and save city employees $567,000 on premiums during calendar year 2014, when compared to
               projections under the current model.  Overall, the transition is projected to save Consortium
               members, their employees, and participating retirees $5.3 million in calendar year 2014.  No
               changes are expected in how employees will access healthcare services due to this transition.

               Over the last two years, the city has taken on the burden for the majority of healthcare
               premium cost increases.  In both FY 2012 and FY 2013, no cost increases were passed on to
               employees in the Value Plan despite 6.4 and 7.7 percent premium increases respectively.
               Employees in the Plus Plan were only passed on half of the premium increases.  The city picked
               up the additional costs in an effort to lessen the burden of the economic downturn on our
               employees.

               Even though the city and its partners have successfully taken steps to limit the premium
               increase, employees will be asked to contribute their share of the additional 8.2 percent in FY
               2014.  On average, beginning in Fall 2013, city employees currently enrolled in healthcare will
               pay an additional $13.70/month (or 22 percent) towards the average premium increase of
               $61.82/month.  The city will pick up costs for the remaining 78 percent of the premium
               increase.

               LIFELONG LEARNING
               The priority of   Lifelong Learning   ensures residents of all ages are able to reach their full
               potential, achieve personal goals, and support a prosperous economy through the development
                                                       .
               of knowledge, skills, abilities, and talents  Lifelong Learning is one of two priority areas that we
               are focusing on during the upcoming fiscal year.

               Norfolk Public Schools
               An excellent educational system is an asset to any community.  We look forward to continuing
               to work with NPS as they develop short and long-range plans to improve achievement for all
               students.  NPS has more resources to educate students in the upcoming fiscal year than in FY
               2013. The Proposed FY 2014 Operating Budget for NPS is $307.9 million.

               The  Commonwealth  ties  its  funding  for  education  to  student  enrollment.  Average  Daily
               Membership (ADM) is the student enrollment count that determines most state funds.  As
               student enrollment declines, so does state support.  This is not the case with city funds.  Even
               during difficult times, city support continues to increase.  I am proposing to increase local

                                                                                                    14



 = Page 14 =








               support by $6.3 million or 5.9 percent, with $3.3 million of that being dedicated to the school
               Construction, Technology, and Infrastructure (CTI) program.

                                   Norfolk Public Schools (NPS) Proposed FY 2014 Budget
                                                                                                  Proposed
                                                 Sources
                                                                                                    Budget
                 Revenue from the City                                                        $110,186,600
                 Revenue from the Commonwealth                                                $180,303,062
                 Revenue from Federal Funds                                                     $4,545,721

                 Revenue from Other Funds                                                       $4,177,226
                 Carryforwards                                                                  $5,400,000
                 Subtotal Operating Funds                                                     $304,612,609

                 Construction, Technology and Infrastructure (CTI)                              $3,330,000

                 Total Local support with CTI                                                 $113,516,600
                 Total Operating including CTI                                                $307,942,609

                 Grant Revenues and Child Nutrition Funds                                      $49,371,032

                 Total Funds                                                                  $357,313,641
                 Additional city services contributed to NPS  (debt service on school
                 buildings and school buses, school resource officers, school crossing         $16,760,267
                 guards, school nurses, grounds and facility maintenance; does not
                 include school construction)
                 Total NPS Budget                                                             $374,073,908

               The Superintendent’s Proposed Budget did not request additional funding from the city.  The
               School Board did, resulting in a $7.3 million request.  I recommend addressing this request, in
               part, through an additional $3.0 million for the Operating Fund.  This $3.0 million was not easy
               to find.  Because we believe our schools are one of our top priorities, we specifically identified
               savings within current operations to transfer to NPS.



                 School Board's FY 2014 request for additional city support/ budget gap         (7,259,673)
                 Increase city contribution                                                     $1,000,000
                 Transfer Public Health School Nurse savings to NPS                               $250,000

                 One-time funding from city savings initiative (decentralize Storehouse)        $1,750,000
                                                    Total additional city operating support     $3,000,000





                                                                                                    15



 = Page 15 =








               In addition to the $3.0 million in additional local support, strategies have been identified to
               close the remaining gap.

                 Meeting the Remaining Gap                                                      (4,259,673)
                 Potential Strategies to meet NPS Gap

                                                         st
                         Delay salary increase to January 1                                     $2,100,000
                         Outsource Custodial Services                                           $2,500,000

                                                                          Total Strategies      $4,600,000

                 Remaining Gap                                                                           $0
                 Potential Surplus                                                                $340,327


               Recommended Strategies:

                       NPS delay the proposed two percent salary increases for employees until January 1,
                       2014.  The delay in salary increases will save approximately $2.1 million, but will still
                       allow the school division to receive approximately $2.0 million in revenue from the state
                       for the salary increase.  This change will also keep the city and school division on par
                                                                                                 st
                       with both city and school employees’ receiving salary increases on January 1 .

                       NPS analyze outsourcing custodial services to realize savings.  According to a proposal it
                       is estimated that NPS can save approximately $2.5 million by outsourcing its custodial
                       services.  The city has outsourced custodial services producing a savings of $1.0 million
                       annually.

               School divisions throughout the Commonwealth are implementing efficiency reviews to find
               savings that can be redirected to classroom instruction.  Suffolk is staggering its school schedule
               resulting in a savings of approximately $895,000, and Virginia Beach is implementing a hybrid
               high school schedule to provide additional opportunities for students that will save at least $1.1
               million.  Richmond  has  an  ‘Accountability  and  Efficiency’  taskforce.    This  taskforce
               recommended $11.8 million in cost savings strategies for FY 2014, including the closure of two
               elementary schools.

               NPS can also analyze the following items during the upcoming year: align healthcare costs to be
               more like the city’s (currently NPS pays a higher share of costs than the city); realign staff to
               meet enrollment decline based on Superintendent’s Proposed Budget; similar to city practices,
               phase in additional personnel based on the ability to fill positions; review existing contracts,
               close out old accounts for projects that are no longer necessary, and implement spending
               controls; close underutilized schools; and share services with the city for communications, fleet,
               printing, and purchasing.


                                                                                                    16



 = Page 16 =








                                School Capital
                                Over the past decade, the city provided support to construct Norview High,
                                Blair Middle, Coleman Place Elementary, and most recently Crossroads K-8.
                                As you can see, the city has always been committed to building schools. The
                                city  has  four  more  schools  to  building  from  its  original  five  school
                                commitment. As such, school construction remains a high priority in the FY
                                2014 Capital Improvement Plan (CIP). The Approved FY 2013 CIP Budget
                                included funds to construct the second and third schools and begin designing
                                the fourth and fifth schools in FY 2016.  What  was not  included was funding to
                                begin construction in FY 2017.


                                          The Proposed FY 2014 Budget continues the commitment to build
                                          five schools at an accelerated rate.  The proposed two-cent real
                                          estate tax increase will be dedicated to schools and will fund the
                                          school CTI program.  With the help of the CTI, the city will be able to
                                          fund the design and construction of the next four schools at a faster
                                          rate than previously planned.    The program will be used solely for
                                          one-time capital, technology, and infrastructure improvements for
                                          the school division.

               The program will be monitored to ensure funding from the tax increase is used solely in support
               of the CTI.  In FY 2014, $3.3 million will be allocated to the CTI lockbox.

               The CTI will (in priority order):


                       1. Pay the debt service payments for school construction projects

                       2. Pay for technology to enhance learning within the classroom

                       3. Provide additional funding to improve infrastructure

               The first school, Crossroads K-8, opened in the fall of 2012.  As I just mentioned, with the help
               of the CTI, the Proposed Five-Year CIP includes funds to design and construct the next four
               schools.  In total, the Five-Year CIP includes $121.0 million in support of school capital projects.
               In addition to the school construction projects, the Five-Year CIP includes funding to address
               school major maintenance, to build a field house, to plan for a new Governor’s school, and to
               support the construction of Camp Allen Elementary through a Department of Defense (DoD)
               federal grant.  The DoD is supporting at least 80 percent of the total estimated cost of $28.7
               million on a reimbursement basis. The city's estimated total contribution will be $5.7 million
               after the reimbursement.






                                                                                                    17



 = Page 17 =








                          Proposed FY 2014 Five-Year Capital Improvement Plan (CIP) (in millions)
                                                                Fiscal Year

                                                                                           Five-Year
                                         Prior                                               Plan
               Project                             2014    2015     2016    2017   2018                 Total
                                        Funding                                            FY 2014-FY
                                                                                             2018
               Crossroads                $29.4                                                          $29.4
               (Opened Fall 2012)
               Campostella               $4.7       $12.3    $5.0                               $17.3   $22.0
                                                                                                                      Five Schools
               Broad Creek Area          $4.7       $12.3    $5.0                               $17.3   $22.0

               Larchmont                                             $2.2  $14.8    $5.0        $22.0   $22.0
               Ocean View                                            $2.2  $14.8    $5.0        $22.0   $22.0

               Subtotal                  $38.9    $24.6    $10.0    $4.4    $29.6    $10     $78.6     $117.5

               Maintenance                         $3.0     $3.0    $3.0    $2.0   $2.0      $13.0     $13.0

               Field House                         $0.5                                      $0.5       $0.5

               Camp Allen
               Elementary
               (20% - city, 80% -                  $4.0    $17.0    $7.7                     $28.7     $28.7
               federal)

               New Governor’s school                        $0.3                             $0.3       $0.3

               Grand Total               $38.9    $32.1    $30.3   $15.1   $31.6  $12.0     $121.0     $159.9

               Note: Amounts may not sum due to rounding.

               Public Safety Internship Program
               An internal initiative in the Proposed FY 2014 Budget is expansion of internship opportunities in
               Public Safety for high school and college students.  This proposal identifies unique internship
               opportunities for young men and women interested in careers in Police, Fire or Emergency
               Communications. The program will promote diversity and retention of qualified candidates for
               careers in public safety.  In partnership with Norfolk State University (NSU) and Tidewater
               Community College (TCC), the Police Department will work to attract and retain ten qualified
               college graduates as police recruit candidates.  The program will provide the students with
               opportunities for skill development in the areas of firearms and defensive tactics while still in
               school.  Upon graduation from NSU and TCC, successful interns will be accepted into the Police
               Academy.  A $10,000 stipend will be provided to eligible candidates over a three year period.

               The Department of Fire-Rescue’s proposed Public Safety Internship program is structured to
               identify two qualified Norfolk youths who have an interest in becoming a Norfolk Firefighter.
               After entering the program, interns will participate in the Academy and upon completion, be
               offered a full-time Firefighter position.


                                                                                                    18



 = Page 18 =









               The Office of Emergency Preparedness and Response (EOC) is working in partnership with Old
               Dominion University and TCC.    The EOC will work to attract and retain one qualified college
               graduate as a candidate.  The program will provide the student with opportunities for skill
               development in the areas of emergency management and disaster planning.

               Urban Youth Summer Academy
               The Proposed Budget supports a new community collaborative
               on the Southside.  Regent University is leading a collaborative
               effort  with  Southside  residents  to  provide  expanded
               educational opportunities for youth.  The ‘Urban Youth Summer
               Academy’ is a three week enrichment program for rising sixth graders that is designed to assist
               them in making a smooth transition to middle school.  The program will expose youth to higher
               education, empowering students toward positive citizenship and community involvement.


               Norfolk Emerging Leaders
               Support continues for the Norfolk Emerging Leaders (NEL) Program, one of the
               premier learning opportunities for high school and college students to gain
               meaningful exposure to careers in public service.  The NEL program provides
               more than 200 high school and college students the opportunity to work side-
               by-side with experienced municipal employees in a variety of programs and
               service areas.

               Norfolk Youth Leadership Program
               The Proposed Budget continues the partnership established last year with NPS
               to conduct a three day, two night camp with the goal of energizing students
               with a passion for leadership not just within their schools, but in their communities as well.

               ECONOMIC VITALITY AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT

               The priority of Economic Vitality and Workforce Development focuses attention and resources
               on a growing and diversified economy that enhances the quality of life for citizens through a
               wide  range  of  housing,  shopping,  educational,  cultural,  business,  and  employment
               opportunities.  Norfolk is unique with nearly 37 percent of all property in the city identified as
               tax exempt (e.g., Naval Base, the Port, universities).  To grow the local economy, we are raising
               the bar on collaboration and customer service.  Our vision can be stated simply: Norfolk will
               create an economic climate that fosters collaboration, innovation, and economic success.  We
               can achieve this objective by creating new and expanding existing partnerships that result in a
               more focused approach to economic and community development.  We will also focus on
               leveraging resources to achieve common goals with our partners.

               Smart Processing
               The Department of Development, the Department of Planning and Community Development,
               and  the  reconfigured  Department  of  Communications  and  Technology  are  working

                                                                                                    19



 = Page 19 =








               collaboratively on the Smart Processing initiative.  Funding in the
               amount of $500,000 has been proposed to promote exceptional
               customer service by ensuring businesses and homeowners have a
               seamless experience while going through the city’s development
               process.  Over the next year, the city will work to create a ‘one-
               stop’  service  center  for  development  related  permits  to  help  improve  processing  times,
               eliminate redundancy and establish an image of certainty and efficiency in the community.
               Additionally,  a  streamlined  permit  process  will  allow  Norfolk  to  remain  competitive  and
               attractive to expanding as well as new business ventures.    To this end, the Proposed Budget
               includes increases to Planning fees that will be reinvested back into the Smart Processing
               initiatives for technology improvements.  These technology improvements will facilitate online
               submission of plans, enhanced permit tracking and provide
               for an expedited permitting process.

               In addition, to provide our businesses the highest level of
               services  possible  in  support  of  reinvestment  and  new
               investment into the local economy, this budget proposes instituting concierge services in the
               Department of Development.  The goal of creating a concierge service program is to:

                       Provide customized customer care service to foster a business friendly environment
                       Focus on collaboration to grow locally owned businesses
                       Expand emphasis to support businesses in our neighborhood business districts
                       Provide exceptional customer service in business development, permitting, and business
                       retention processes

               ACCESSIBILITY, MOBILITY AND CONNECTIVITY
                                                         The  priority  of  Accessibility,  Mobility  and
                                                         Connectivity  focuses  attention  and  resources  on
                                                         instituting a comprehensive system of accessibility
                                                         options,  addressing  all  traditional  transportation
                                                         modes as well as new technologies, that connect
                                                         people, goods, and information.  The Proposed FY
                                                         2014 Budget incorporates programs and activities
                                                         that  improve  transportation  linkages,  connect
               people and communities, and ensure Norfolk’s business services are supported by a reliable

               technology infrastructure.

               Work continues on improving transportation options for Norfolk residents, businesses and
               visitors.  Construction of the Intercity Passenger Rail Facility at Harbor Park is scheduled for
               completion in September 2013.  The 3,500 square foot facility is within walking distance to the
               Harbor Park Light Rail Station.  Additionally, other alternative transportation modes such as
               bicycling are beginning to take hold.  Investments in bicycle infrastructure include improving
               bicycle roadway safety and increasing the number of secured bicycle parking spaces citywide.

                                                                                                    20



 = Page 20 =








               These types of activities are the work of direct collaboration with residents and businesses to
               make Norfolk a bicycle friendly community.

               We are also working to address the backlog of citywide technology projects in the Proposed FY
               2014 Budget.  These projects include the scheduled laptop replacement for Police and Fire
               vehicles and the citywide computer and server replacement projects.  Keeping our technology
               infrastructure up to date is an important component of maintaining efficient operations.  While
               we may need to provide additional funding to make this happen, we will recoup the savings
               over time and avoid increased costs by putting them off.

               One component of our technology infrastructure that we can no longer wait to fund is
               increasing internet bandwidth and system redundancy to improve reliability.  The Proposed FY
               2014 Budget includes a plan to purchase internet services from a second service provider.
               Currently, Cox Communications is the sole internet provider for all city departments and
               agencies.  This plan provides additional bandwidth to support new applications and new
               facilities coming online, such as the Slover Library and the combined courthouse.  Just as
               important as increasing bandwidth and redundancy, this plan ensures reliable service even
               during a catastrophic event.

               ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY
               The priority of Environmental Sustainability focuses on maintaining the community’s status as a
               premier waterfront community that thrives economically and culturally, avoids detrimental
               environmental impacts while creating a positive, regenerative effect on its environment. One of
                                         the main environmental sustainability issues the city faces is flooding.
                                         In the Proposed Budget, work continues to address citywide flooding
                                         issues.

                                         The comprehensive approach began in FY 2013 to address both
                                         precipitation and tidal flooding across the entire city.  With the
                                         implementation  of  a  long-term  tidal  and  precipitation  flooding
                                         analysis  as  well  as  a  shoreline  protection  analysis,  the  city  is
               developing solutions for the short-term and long-term. The scope and magnitude of flooding
               issues, as you are already aware, are beyond the fiscal capabilities of the city alone, and as a
               result, we are continuing to work collaboratively with the Army Corps of Engineers and our
               congressional delegation on flooding issues.

               WELL-MANAGED GOVERNMENT
               The priority of Well-Managed Government is to create a data‐driven organization that provides
               effective and efficient city programs and services that are responsive, accountable, inclusive
               and customer-focused.  Having a well-managed government begins with our employees who
               accepted this challenge upon my arrival in 2011.  Employees are doing their part to make our
               organization more efficient and effective by working collaboratively across departmental lines
               to identify more efficient ways of conducting business as well as creating a customer friendly

                                                                                                    21



 = Page 21 =








               environment for conducting business throughout the city.  These efforts have led to higher
               efficiency levels, elimination of redundant processes, and reductions in cost of service.

               A Conservative Approach to Staffing
               This Proposed Budget has taken a conservative approach to staffing.  Other than those related
               to the opening of the Slover Memorial Library and the reorganization creating the Department
               of  Communications  and  Technology,  the  Proposed  Budget  includes  no  new  permanent
               positions in the General Fund.  Additionally, we have worked to achieve $1.6 million in targeted
               personnel reductions.  The majority of the $1.6 million was achieved by eliminating vacant
               positions and attempting to more accurately project future attrition rates based on historical
               data.  Overall, the Proposed FY 2014 Budget includes 30 fewer permanent positions in the
               General Fund than FY 2013.

               Fleet Management
               One area of the organization where we will continue to look to improve operations in FY 2014 is
               Fleet Management.  The restructuring of Fleet continues to promote additional operating
               efficiencies and employ industry best practices.  During FY 2013, Fleet Management’s Parts
               Room was outsourced, creating ongoing savings and allowing for the just-in-time delivery of
               parts.  Additionally, the execution of a body shop contract, the implementation of fixed price
               fuel contracts and the standardization of staff schedules have all increased efficiencies while
               keeping costs in line.

               Employer of Choice
               There are not enough words to express my gratitude to the employees
               who work so hard to make Norfolk a special place.  Each and every day,
               our  men  and  women  put  their  lives  on  the  line,  make  personal
               sacrifices, and bring a commitment to excellence to their jobs.

               The  Proposed  FY  2014  Budget  continues  support  for  our  employees’  work  through  the
               Employer of Choice initiative, which was created to attract and retain an engaged and dynamic
               workforce.  The Employer of Choice initiative, announced in the Proposed FY 2013 Budget,
               included more than just compensation and benefits.  A major focus of the Employer of Choice
               concept is providing opportunities for employees to strengthen their skills for professional
               growth  and  development,  as  well  as  offer  opportunities  for  cross  training  and  career
               advancement. The Proposed FY 2014 Budget supports efforts begun in FY 2013 including:

                       Tuition reimbursement
                       Employer and supervisor training opportunities
                       Four hours to volunteer at NPS
                       Master Police and Firefighter programs

               Additionally, new for FY 2014 is the creation of additional public safety internship opportunities
               for NPS students and a two percent General Wage Increase (GWI) for all employees beginning

                                                                                                    22



 = Page 22 =








               January 2014.  We would like to do more to reward our employees for their hard work, but
               financial constraints limit our abilities.

               Also, in the upcoming fiscal year, we will undertake a comprehensive review of the city’s overall
               compensation plan for employees.  This review will examine best practices as they relate to
               compensation, additional retirement benefits such as the Deferred Retirement Option Program,
               retirement contributions, compensation and benefits for permanent full-time employees in the
               city’s lowest pay grades, and conduct a full review of the appropriateness of the Step system.

               SAFE, HEALTHY AND INCLUSIVE COMMUNITIES
               The priority of Safe, Healthy and Inclusive Communities is to ensure
               residents of diverse backgrounds and interests feel empowered to
               come together to assist in the development of safe and healthy
               neighborhoods that foster a sense of well‐being, and make Norfolk a
               fun place to live, work, and play.  Work continues on efforts to
               improve the quality of life in Norfolk neighborhoods.  The Neighbors
               Building Neighborhoods initiative is being replicated throughout the
               city and its results to date have attracted the attention of the
               Hampton  Roads  Community  Foundation.    The  Foundation,  in
               partnership  with  the  Park  Place  neighborhood,  is  proposing  to
               create a 501(c)(3) to continue the work begun under the Greater
               Park  Place  Visioning  and  Engagement  Process.    As  proposed,  this  initiative  will  leverage
               community based resources to meet the specific needs of Norfolk neighborhoods.

               Norfolk is an active participant in the Better Block Project, which is a best practice initiative
               that rebuilds an area using grassroots efforts to show the potential to create a great
               walkable,  vibrant  neighborhood  center.  The  project  acts  as  a  living  charrette  so  that
               communities can actively engage in the "complete streets" build out process and develop
               pop-up businesses to show the potential for revitalized economic activity in an area.  Initial
               efforts in FY 2013 were positive and the program provides an inexpensive way to create
               excitement around community projects.

               A collaborative effort with other Hampton Roads cities and Virginia Supportive Housing is
               underway to begin the planning for a second single room occupancy apartment complex in
               Norfolk.  When completed, the proposed facility will be the sixth in Hampton Roads modeled
                                                                                                   th
               after the successful 80 unit Gosnold Apartment Complex located at Gosnold and 25  Street in
               Park Place.

               CAPITAL IMPROVEMENT PROGRAM
                The city’s CIP has served as an important tool for improving not only investment in bricks and
               mortar, but also supporting activities that promote and sustain our overall quality of life.
               Before  we  look  ahead  to  current  and  future  projects,  we  should  understand  how  past
               investments have benefited our community.  Since 2000, the city has authorized over $1.0

                                                                                                    23



 = Page 23 =








               billion  to  improve  our  schools,  neighborhoods,  public  buildings  including  libraries  and
               recreation  centers,  as  well  as  repairing  and  replacing  the  aged  water  and  wastewater
               infrastructure.

               Moreover, the city’s investment has leveraged work in the private sector to improve the quality
               of life in Norfolk’s Neighborhoods that has included the following developments: Berkley
               Shopping Center that is anchored by a Farm Fresh Grocery Store; the East Beach community;
               YMCA  in  Park  Place;  the  public-private  redevelopment  of  Broad  Creek;  and  the  Military
               Highway commercial corridor.

               Our CIP functions similar to a credit card.  We can buy things today with the promise to repay
               the lender in the future.  While the initial payment to finance the cost of CIP projects may be
               low, as borrowing increases, the payments continue to grow.  Continual borrowing eventually
               balloons into large annual debt payments years after projects have been approved for funding.
               Our efforts in prior years to address capital needs through borrowing are now limiting the city’s
               ability to address new capital infrastructure projects.

               The city’s General Fund CIP is guided by two measures of affordability; one measure is tied to
               the value of revenue producing real property and the second measure is tied to a proportionate
               share of the General Fund budget.  These measures, or self-imposed debt limits, are as follows:

                       Debt Service as a percent of the General Fund budget (not-to-exceed 10 percent)
                       Net debt as a percent of taxable real estate (not-to-exceed 3.5 percent)

                The city will be challenged to stay within these measures as we move forward through the next
               five years.

                The city’s General Fund planned projects in the Proposed FY 2014 Budget increase by $16.1
               million from $70.7 million to $86.8 million.  School capital funding and the courthouse complex
               comprise 62 percent of the FY 2014 Proposed General Capital CIP.  Even with the ongoing
               funding challenges in our CIP, as a community there is agreement on the urgency to accelerate
               the construction of school buildings to enhance the learning environment for Norfolk’s children.
               The proposed two-cent real estate tax increase addresses the critical construction, technology,
               and  infrastructure  needs  of  NPS  by  allowing  us  to  fund  the  construction of  the  fourth,
               Larchmont Elementary, and fifth, Ocean View Elementary, schools in FY 2017.  Moving forward
               with school projects, however, will not relieve the city of other capital obligations related to the
               citywide infrastructure replacement and repair backlog that we have put off in the past few
               years.

                The city, even with these constraints must continue to address neighborhood needs and
               infrastructure backlog by allocating appropriate resources to repair, renovate and replace
               existing facilities.  The Proposed CIP restores funding for the neighborhood plans for Broad
                                                                                                    24



 = Page 24 =








               Creek, Fairmount Park, Southside and Wards Corner.  Additionally, we cannot put off the
               infrastructure needs of our public facilities any further.  As such, funding is provided to address
               the city’s aged infrastructure to extend the useful life of existing buildings.

                                        FY 2014 Capital Improvement Plan
                          Courthouse
                            Project                  Major Categories                       Lifelong
                            $26.4                                                          Learning
                             30%                                                             $32.1
                                                                                             37%












                         Neighborhoods                                                Public Buildings
                         / Infrastructure                                                 / Other
                             $12.0                                                         $16.3
                              14%                        Amounts in millions               19%

                                                          Amounts in millions
               The backlog of work required on city buildings includes fire stations.  The Proposed FY 2014 CIP
               accelerates the construction schedule for two fire stations that are operating beyond their
               useful lifecycle.  These two stations were originally built as horse-drawn engine companies; Fire
               Station #12, built in 1924 (89 years old), is located on W. Little Creek Road and Fire Station #11,
               built in 1925 (88 years old), is located on Verdun Avenue.  The Proposed CIP budget moves
               design of Station #12 into FY 2014, with construction scheduled for FY 2015.  Design of Station
               #11 is scheduled to begin in FY 2015, with construction scheduled for FY 2016.

               The rebuilding of these two fire stations will address multiple issues with operating a modern
               fire-rescue  operation  in  an  antiquated  building,  including  difficulties  locating  equipment,
               outdated building ventilation systems, and inadequate living quarters that currently do not
               meet the needs of firefighters.  A key to the success of this capital project is the patience
               displayed by our firefighters in waiting for these projects to get off the ground.  I want to thank
               each and every firefighter for continuing to carry out their duties in a professional manner in
               spite of the issues they face working in these two facilities.

               Similarly, the city’s Recreation and Parks system is in need of additional investment to address
               an aging infrastructure.  Under the theme of ‘Refresh, Reconnect and Refocus’, the Recreation
               and Parks Master Plan provides a blueprint for improving offerings at city parks, recreation
               centers, and playgrounds.  The Master Plan focuses on the infrastructure backlog through the
               renovation of existing facilities, with a special emphasis placed on necessary repairs and
               upgrades.  The estimated price tag of the Recreation and Parks Master Plan is $138 million.

                                                                                                    25



 = Page 25 =








               While it will take many years to address the needs identified in the plan, we must address the
               infrastructure.

               CONCLUSIONSANDNEXTSTEPS



               The Proposed FY 2014 Budget continues the process of building a well-managed government.
               As  we  move  forward, there  are new  initiatives  we  will  undertake  to  improve  operating
               efficiencies in the next fiscal year by completing a comprehensive revision of the city’s financial
               practices and policies.

               Also, as part of this review and looking ahead to FY 2015 and beyond, the city’s budget
               allocation  decisions  will  increasingly  be  impacted  by  costs  that  are  resistant  to  change
               including:  debt  service,  health  insurance,  retirement,  and  funding  reserves.    Identifying
               appropriate measures to minimize the impacts of these items on future budgets is a priority.
               Similarly, we will examine personnel packages including a review of various models and best
               practices that coincide with our efforts to become an Employer of Choice.

               Additionally, to achieve long-term fiscal sustainability, throughout FY 2014 the city will continue
               its review of operations that receive city subsidies: Cemeteries, Fleet Management, and Golf.
               Review of these operations were discussed in FY 2013 and work has begun to examine options
               for improving the effectiveness of each operation as well as identifying alternative methods for
               providing services or determining if the program can be contracted out.  These actions are
               required in order to determine future courses of action, to strengthen financial resources, and
               to deliver levels of service to meet the needs of Norfolk’s residents, businesses and visitors.

               Finally, we must keep a close eye on Washington as the impacts of Sequestration loom on the
               horizon.    We  will  make  necessary  adjustments  as  more  information  becomes  available.
               However, it should be noted, that unlike other cities, we do not have additional resources to
               put aside funds to cushion potential losses in federal revenue.  Our only alternative will be to
               either cut existing programs or reprogram funding to support the highest priorities.

               Even as we discuss issues such as Sequestration, this financial plan, as proposed, provides the
               necessary elements to keep us on the path to being a well-managed government. We look
               forward to working with  the Council and the community to implement these strategies.
               Furthermore, it is our belief that these initiatives will lay the groundwork necessary to support
               the overall quality of life of this great city.











                                                                                                    26



 = Page 26 =
