



                          Strategic Plan
                                Mission
                                We work in partnership with
                                all citizens to achieve a
                                quality Community.








                                Values

                                Integrity
                                  Earning confidence and respect by aligning our values, words and actions
                                Collaboration
                                  Making better decisions by building partnerships and sharing knowledge and resources
                                Excellence
                                  Providing outstanding customer service by striving to be the best in everything we do
                                Stewardship
                                  Improving our quality of life by safeguarding
                                  and enhancing the resources
                                  entrusted to us






                                Vision

                                We are a historic place
                                  James City County recognizes its unique historic identity as the site of the first permanent
                                  English speaking colony in 1607, the first business enterprise, and the beginning of representative
                                  government in America. We are a community that preserves and protects its irreplaceable assets
                                  for current and future generations and for visitors from around the world.
                                We value healthy minds and healthy bodies
                                  James City County is a community that values and supports a high-performance education
                                  system for its children and adults as well as lifelong learning opportunities for all. We have
                                  easy access to a range of quality health care and a quality park and recreation system and
                                  leisure opportunities to promote wellness.
                                We have a special character
                                  James City County is known for its beauty as reflected in open spaces, vistas and the health of
                                  its ecosystems. We have a sense of community because there is a range of quality housing that
                                  is thoughtfully and logically placed and developed with sustainability in mind. Our community
                                  feels safe in its neighborhoods, which are attractive, pleasant and welcoming places to live.
                                  Business and industry add to our character and want to locate and grow here. We are economically
                                  strong with a stable tax base and meaningful jobs. We have a safe, efficient multimodal
                                  transportation network that is interconnected with the rest of Hampton Roads and Virginia.
                                We are a community of choice
                                  James City County is the County of choice for people of many income levels, cultures
                                  and ethnicities.
                                We have first-class government
                                  James City County Government focuses on the needs of the community by fostering citizen
                                  participation and involvement in local government. By maintaining a well-trained, professional
                                  and ethical staff, we continually strive to make James City County the best community to live,
                                  work and visit.

                                                               i

 = Page 1 =
