

                Williamsburg Regional Library System                            General Operating Fund

                and Arts Center



               DESCRIPTION OF SERVICES

               The Williamsburg Regional Library consists of two Mobile Library Services vehicles and two buildings -
               the James City County Library on Croaker Road and the Williamsburg Library on Scotland Street.  The
               Library offers a wide range of materials for adults and children.  In addition to books, the Library
               provides audio books on CD, feature and non-feature videos and DVDs, music CDs, and several specialty
               collections.  The Library also provides access to numerous online computer resources. Librarians are
               available to assist users at our buildings and remotely via phone, E-mail, or instant messaging. The
               Mobile Library Services vehicles bring Library resources to community members who cannot access the
               Library buildings.  The Library also provides a homebound service, delivering materials to those unable
               to take advantage of the Mobile Library Services vehicles.  The Library offers an assortment of programs
               for children and adults, including story times, Library tours, computer classes, and book discussions.  The
               Library hosts the acclaimed Dewey Decibel Concert Series, regular films, exhibits, and other events.  The
               Williamsburg Library has three meeting rooms and a 268-seat theater; the James City County Library has
               two meeting rooms, a computer lab, and the 90-seat Kitzinger Community Room.  Through formal
               partnerships with 26 local organizations, the Library extends its reach into the community, attracting new
               users and expanding access to Library services.

               BUDGET SUMMARY

                                                   FY 12             FY 13              FY 14
                                                  Adopted           Adopted              Plan

                  Regional Library System &
                                Arts Center   $    4,067,456   $     4,120,251    $    4,160,253

               Total Regional Library System Budget:

                                                   FY 12             FY 13              FY 14
                                                  Adopted           Adopted              Plan

                                    County    $    4,067,456   $     4,120,251    $    4,160,253
                                      City          779,369            819,506           840,552
                                     Other          955,338            782,157           988,528
                                      Total   $    5,802,163   $     5,721,914    $    5,989,333

               BUDGET COMMENTS

               The City of Williamsburg and the County have a contractual agreement for the operations of the library
               system. The contract provides for Library employees to be covered under the County’s personnel and pay
               plans.  This budget provides for increased County funding as per the contractual agreement as a result of
               the change in VRS funding.  Other funding for the Regional Library System decreases due to lower State
               Aid and decreased collections in Library fines and interest earnings.









                                                           Page C-49


 = Page 1 =
