











                                                Glossary

 = Page 1 =














































                                      This page intentionally left blank

 = Page 2 =




            G  LOSSARY




            Account:  A record of public funds showing receipts, disbursements, and the balance.


            Accounting Basis:  The basis of accounting determines rules for recognition of income, expense, assets, liabilities
            and equity (cash basis and accrual basis are the most widely known).  The City of Norfolk operates on a budgetary
            basis under which most expenditure liabilities are recognized when incurred and most revenues are recognized
            when earned and billed.  Adjustments from this budgetary basis are done for financial reporting purposes to
            conform to Generally Accepted Accounting Principles (GAAP).

            Accrual Accounting:  A generally accepted accounting method where revenue is recognized when earned and
            expenses when incurred.  These revenues and expenses are recorded at the end of an accounting period even if
            cash has not been received or paid.


            ADA (Americans with Disabilities Act):  Federal legislation that prohibits discrimination and ensures equal
            opportunity for persons with disabilities in employment, state and local government services, public
            accommodations, commercial facilities, and transportation.


            ADM (Average Daily Membership):    ADM is the total days in membership for all students over the school year
            divided by the number of days school was in session.  This number is used by the state to calculate annual funding
            levels for local public schools.

            Ad Valorem tax:  A tax based upon the assessed value of real estate or personal property.


            Annual Plan:  A plan that identifies the annual funding of the city’s priority community development projects and
            activities as outlined in the five-year Consolidated Plan.

            Appropriation:  An expenditure authorization granted by the City Council to incur obligations for specific
            purposes.  Appropriations are usually limited to amount, purpose and time.


            Approved Budget:   The budget as formally adopted by City Council with legal appropriations for the upcoming
            fiscal year.

            Assessed Valuation : The estimated dollar value placed upon real and personal property by the City Real Estate
            Assessor and Commissioner of the Revenue, respectively, as the basis for levying property taxes.  Real property is
            required to be assessed at full market value.   Varying methodologies are used for assessment of defined classes of
            personal property to ensure uniformity and approximate fair market value.


            Balanced budget:  A budget in which current expenditures are supported by current revenues.

            Bond indenture:  The formal agreement between a group of bond holders, acting through a trustee, and the issuer
            as to the term and security for the debt.








                                                                                                         Glossary   563

 = Page 3 =





        Bond Rating:  In rating municipalities for the issuance of general obligation debt, credit rating agencies (Standard
        and Poor’s, Moody’s, Fitch) consider factors that are considered especially relevant to a government’s “capacity and
        willingness” to repay its debt:  The local economic base, including local employment, taxes, and demographics (for
        example, age, education, income level, and skills of the local population);  Financial performance and flexibility,
        including accounting and reporting methods, revenue and expenditure structure and patterns, annual operating
        and budgetary performance, financial leverage and equity position, budget and financial planning, and
        contingency financial obligations, such as pension liability funding;  Debt burden; and  Administration, including
        local autonomy and discretion regarding financial affairs, background and experience of key administrative
        officials, and frequency of elections.  Bond ratings impact the interest rate and the cost of debt service in the
        operating budget.

        Bonds:  A type of security sold to finance capital improvement projects.  With “general obligation” bonds, the full
        faith and credit of the city, through its taxing authority, guarantee the principal and interest payments.  The City of
        Norfolk has issued water and parking revenue bonds for which repayment is pledged from the revenues of those
        systems.


        Budget:  A financial plan for a specified period of time (fiscal year) that matches all planned revenues with
        expenditures for various municipal services.


        CAFR (Comprehensive Annual Financial Report):    The official annual financial report of the city.  It includes
        financial statements prepared in conformity with GAAP and is organized into a financial reporting pyramid.  It also
        includes supporting schedules necessary to demonstrate compliance with finance-related legal and contractual
        provisions, required supplementary information, extensive introduction material and illustrative information about
        the city.

        CAD (Computer Aided Dispatch System):    Computer systems supporting the Emergency Operations Center 911
        response service areas as well as other areas of public safety.


        CADD (Computer Aided Design and Drafting System):     Computer systems with input-tools for the purpose of
        streamlining drafting, documentation and design processes.

        Capital Lease:  A direct substitute for purchase of an asset with borrowed money. It is a non-cancelable contract to
        make a series of payments in return for use of an asset for a specified period of time. It transfers substantially all the
        benefits and risks inherent in the ownership of the property to the lessee.


        Capital Outlay:  Expenditures that result in the acquisition of or addition to, fixed assets.  Fixed assets generally are
        purchased from the Equipment appropriation category to facilitate the maintenance of the fixed assets inventory.

        Capital Projects:  Projects for the purchase or construction of capital assets.  Typically, a capital project
        encompasses a purchase of land and/or the construction of a building or facility.


        CAPER (Comprehensive Annual Performance Evaluation Report):      The CAPER is the annual report prepared
        annually in compliance with grant funding requirements to the federal Department of Housing and Urban
        Development (HUD) for the Community Development Block Grant program, the HOME Investment Partnership
        Program and the Emergency Shelter Grant (ESG) program.




        564   Glossary

 = Page 4 =





            Categorical Aid:   Revenue received from the state or federal government designated for specific use by the local
            government.  Examples of state categorical aid are Basic School Aid funds and the state's share of public assistance
            payments.  An example of federal categorical aid is Impacted Area Aid grants that are to be used for education.


            CDBG (Community Development Block Grant):     A federal funding source that allows local officials and residents
            flexibility in designing their own programs within a wide-range of eligible activities.  The goal of the CDBG
            program is to encourage more broadly conceived community development projects, and expand housing
            opportunities for people living in low and moderate-income households.

            Central Appropriation:   Programs and services the city provides that are not directly linked to specific
            departments, such as employee benefits, risk management, and transfers to other departments.


            Charges for Service:   Fees charged for various government operations that are based on a cost recovery model.
            Examples include garbage fees, sanitation and waste removal fees, parking fees, water fees, and storm water fees.

            CHINS (Children in Need of Services):  Youth that are referred by parents, schools, etc. for diversionary services
            such as family counseling, anger management, truancy prevention, and in some cases temporary residential
            placements.  The goal is to provide services that would result in behavior modification to avoid entry into the
            juvenile justice system.


            CHINSUP   (Children in Need of Supervision): Youth that are placed on court-ordered, supervision after having
            received diversionary services.  These court-ordered, community-based services may be residential or non-
            residential.


            CIP (Capital Improvement Plan):  A five year plan developed to guide spending for capital projects such as
            buildings, parks, streets, etc. and their financing sources. The Capital Improvement Plan (CIP) budget is adopted as
            a one-year appropriation as part of the five-year to authorize expenditures for the projects in the first year of the
            plan.

            Community Development Fund:     A fund that accounts for federal entitlement funds received under Title I of the
            Housing and Community Development Act of 1974.  These Community Development Block Grant (CDBG) funds
            support public improvements and redevelopment and conservation activities within targeted neighborhoods and
            are developed as part of the Annual Plan.


            Compensated Absences:    A liability for vested vacation and sick leave benefits for employees that is recorded as
            general long-term obligations.


            Component Units:   Legally separate entities which are in substance part of the city’s operations.  Component units
            are The School Board of the City of Norfolk, The Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority, and The City of
            Norfolk Retirement Board.

            Consolidated Plan:   A three or five-year plan that describes a community’s needs, resources, priorities, and
            proposed activities to be undertaken with funding provided by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban
            Development (HUD).  The Consolidated Plan must include opportunities for resident input and is updated
            annually.




                                                                                                         Glossary   565

 = Page 5 =





        Constitutional Officers:   Elected officials who head local offices as directed by the Constitution of Virginia.  There
        are five constitutional officers in Norfolk with partial State funding coordinated by the State Compensation Board:
        the Commissioner of Revenue, the City Treasurer, the Clerk of the Circuit Court, the Commonwealth’s Attorney and
        the Sheriff.


        Contingent Fund:    A budgetary account set-aside for use by the City Manager in dealing with emergencies or
        unforeseen expenditures.

        Contractual Service:   Legal agreement between the city and an outside entity providing services that are mutually
        agreed and have binding terms.


        Debt Service:  The annual payment of principal and interest on the city’s bonded indebtedness.

        Debt Service Fund:  The account used for accumulation of resources required for and the payment of principal and
        interest on the current portion of general obligations of the city.


        Deficit:  The excess of an entity's or fund's liabilities over its assets (see Fund Balance).  The excess of expenditures
        or expenses over revenues during a single budget year.

        Depreciation:  Expiration in the service life of capital assets attributable to wear and tear, deterioration, action of
        the physical elements, inadequacy or obsolescence.  That portion of the cost of a capital asset which is charged as
        an expense during a particular period for reporting purposes in proprietary funds (the capital outlay, rather than
        the periodic depreciation expense, is recorded under the modified accrual basis of budgeting and accounting).


        DEQ (Department of Environmental Quality):   The state agency that is dedicated to protecting the environment
        of Virginia in order to promote the health and well-being of the citizens of the Commonwealth.

        Derelict Structure:   Residential or nonresidential building or structure, whether or not construction has been
        completed, that might endanger the public’s health, safety or welfare and for a continuous period in excess of six
        months has been: vacant; boarded up; and not lawfully connected to electric service from a utility service provider
        or not lawfully connected to any water or sewer service from a utility service provider.


        DTO Transactions (Direct Turnover Transactions):  Non-stock items that are specially ordered and turned over
        directly to customers.  Items ordered are not a part of inventory.


        Effectiveness:   The degree to which goals, objectives and outcomes are achieved.

        Efficiency:   A measurement of an organization’s performance based on operational outputs as measured by a
        comparison of production with cost.


        Emergency Communications Center (ECC):     The Emergency Communications Center serves as a central point to
        provide timely, accurate and critical 24-hour communications with all field units (police, fire and other emergency
        services).

        Emergency Operations Center (EOC):    A central command and control facility responsible for carrying out the
        principles of emergency preparedness and emergency management, or disaster management functions at a
        strategic level in an emergency situation, and ensuring the continuity of operations during an emergency.

        566   Glossary

 = Page 6 =





            Encumbrance:   An obligation against budgeted funds in the form of a purchase order, contract, salary
            commitment or other reservation of available funds.


            Enterprise Funds:  A separate fund used to account for operations that are financed and operated in a manner
            similar to private business enterprises and where it is the intent that costs (expenses, including depreciation) of
            providing goods or services to the general public on a continuing basis be financed or recovered primarily through
            user charges.

            Expenditure:  Where accounts are kept on the accrual or modified accrual basis of accounting, the cost of goods
            received or services rendered, whether cash payment has been made or not.  Where accounts are kept on a cash
            basis, expenditure is recognized only when the cash payment is made.


            Fiduciary Funds:   Funds used to account for resources held for the benefit of parties outside the city.  The fiduciary
            funds include the city’s pension trust fund, the Commonwealth of Virginia agency fund and the miscellaneous
            agency fund.

            Financial Policy:  The city’s policy in respect to taxes, spending, and debt management as these relate to the
            provision of city services, programs and capital investment.


            Fines and Forfeitures:   This revenue category includes revenue received by the local government from court fines
            and forfeitures and parking fines.

            Fiscal Year (FY):  A 12-month period to which the annual operating budget applies.  At the end of the period, the
            city determines its financial position and results of its operations.  The city’s fiscal year is July 1 through June 30.


            Fixed Assets:  A long-term tangible piece of property that a firm owns and uses in the production of its income and
            is not expected to be consumed or converted into cash any sooner than one year's time. Buildings, real estate,
            equipment and furniture are examples of fixed assets.  Fixed assets are sometimes collectively referred to as “plant
            facilities.”


            Fleet Management Fund:    A fund used to provide operating departments with maintenance, repair and service
            for the city’s fleet of vehicles, heavy equipment and miscellaneous machinery.

            Freedom of Information Act (FOIA):  State statute that ensures the people of the Commonwealth ready access to
            public records in the custody of a public body or its officers and employees, and free entry to meetings of public
            bodies wherein the business of the people is being conducted.  All public records and meetings shall be presumed
            open, unless an exemption is properly invoked.


            Fringe Benefits:  Employee benefits, in addition to salary, which may be paid in full or in part by the city or
            sponsored for employee participation at their individual expense. Some benefits, such as Social Security and
            Medicare (FICA), unemployment insurance, workers’ compensation, and others are required by law.   Other
            benefits, such as health, dental and life insurance are not mandated by law but are offered to employees by the city
            as part of their total compensation.


            Full-Time Equivalent (FTE):  A term that expresses the amount of time a position has been budgeted for in terms
            of the amount of time a permanent, full-time employee normally works a year.  Most full-time employees are paid


                                                                                                         Glossary   567

 = Page 7 =





        for 2,080 hours a year.  A position that has been budgeted to work less than full-time will work the number of hours
        which equate to that budgeted FTE amount; for example, a half FTE budgeted position can work 40 hours a week
        for six months, or 20 hours a week for one year.


        Fund:  An independent fiscal and accounting entity with a self-balancing set of accounts recording its assets,
        liabilities, and fund balances/retained earnings, and revenues and expenditures/expenses.


        Fund Balances:  In the context of the city’s budget discussions, fund balance generally refers to the undesignated
        General Fund Balance.  This is the accumulated total of all prior years’ actual General Fund revenues in excess of
        expenditures, or “surplus,” that has not been appropriated by City Council and that has not been designated or
        reserved for other uses.  Maintaining a prudent level of undesignated General Fund balance is critical to ensuring
        that the city is able to cope with financial emergencies and fluctuations in revenue cycles.  General Fund balance
        also provides working capital during temporary periods when expenditures exceed revenues.  The undesignated
        General Fund balance is analogous to the retained earnings of proprietary funds.

        GAAP (Generally Accepted Accounting Principles):   The common set of accounting principles, standards, and
        procedures that are used to complete financial statements.


        GASB 34 (Governmental Accounting Standards Board):       A statement that established the financial report
        standards for state and local governments. The financial statements should consist of Management’s discussion
        and analysis, basic financial statements, notes to the financial statements and supplementary information.

        GASB 54 (Governmental Accounting Standards Board):      A statement that established changes to the fund
        balance classifications and governmental fund type definitions.


        GEM Program:   A city initiative operating under the guidelines of Commonwealth of Virginia blight eradication
        legislation (VA Codes 58.1-3970.1 and 58.1-3965), which allows cities to acquire private property where nuisance
        abatement liens and/or delinquent taxes were not paid by their owners.  The GEM Program acquires slum and
        blighting properties in the community to provide opportunities for redevelopment and revitalization of Norfolk’s
        neighborhoods.


        General Fund:  The primary operating fund that accounts for all revenues and expenditures that are not accounted
        for in specific purpose funds.  It finances the regular day-to-day operations of the city with taxes, fees and other
        revenue sources.

        General Obligation Bonds:  General obligation bonds are direct obligations, and they pledge with the full faith
        and credit of the city.


        GIS (Geographic Information System):   A system used to capture, manage, analyze and display all forms of
        geographically referenced information.   A team of employees is responsible for the design and deployment of this
        web-based application that displays information at the street, neighborhood, and planning district levels.

        GFOA   (Government Finance Officers Association):  An organization founded to support the advancement of
        governmental accounting, auditing and financial reporting.






        568   Glossary

 = Page 8 =





            Goal:  A long-range desirable development attained by time phased objectives and designed to carry out a
            strategy.


            GPS (Global Position System):  A system that provides specially coded satellite signals that can be processed in a
            GPS receiver, enabling the receiver to compute position, velocity and time. GPS is funded by and controlled by the
            U. S. Department of Defense (DOD). While there are many thousands of civil users of GPS world-wide, the system
            was designed for and is operated by the U. S. military.

            Grant:  A cash award given by a government to a public agency in a lower level of government or special recipient
            for a specified purpose.  The two major forms of grants are Block and Discretionary or Categorical.  Block Grants are
            awarded primarily to general-purpose governments, are distributed to them according to formulas established in
            the law, and can be used for any locally determined activities that fall within the functional purpose of the grant as
            stated in the law.  Discretionary or Categorical Grants can only be used for a specific purpose and usually are
            limited to narrowly defined projects or activities.

            Grants Fund:  A fund established to account for the receipt and disbursement of revenue from such sources as
            federal and state agencies, adjacent municipalities, and city matching funds.  Individual grants, which typically
            have project periods distinct from the city’s fiscal year, are appropriated by City Council separately when ready for
            application approval and are therefore not included in the annual budget.


            Health Care Fund:  A fund established to account for the receipt and disbursement of revenue from the Norfolk
            Health Consortium members, employees and retirees for payments of claims, administrative costs and other
            expenses related to healthcare.

            Insurance:  A contract to pay a premium in return for which the insurer will pay compensation in certain
            eventualities such as fire, theft, motor accident.  The premiums are calculated so that, on average, they are
            sufficient to pay compensation for the policyholders who will make a claim together with a margin to cover
            administration cost and profit.  In effect, insurance spreads the risk so that the loss by policyholder is compensated
            at the expense of all those who insure against it.

            Internal Service Funds:  Funds that account for the financing of goods and services supplied to other funds of the
            city and other governmental units on a cost-reimbursement basis. The city’s Fleet Management operates as an
            internal service fund.


            Key Goals and Objectives:   A concise presentation of departmental outcome and/or efficiency goals and
            objectives for the budgeted fiscal year.

            Legal Debt Margin:  Limits how much debt an entity can issue. Article VII, Section 10 of the Virginia Constitution
            states: “No city or town shall issue any bonds or other interest-bearing obligations which, including existing
            indebtedness, shall at any time exceed ten percent of the assessed valuation of real estate in the city or town
            subject to taxation, as shown by the last preceding assessment of taxes.”

            Liability Insurance:  Protection against risk of financial loss due to a civil wrong that results in property damage or
            bodily injury.






                                                                                                         Glossary   569

 = Page 9 =





        Line Item:  A budgetary account representing a specific object of expenditure.  Line items are commonly referred
        to as the budget detail and account for the inputs related to an activity process or service.


        Litigation:  To carry on a legal contest by judicial process.


        Local Composite Index (LCI):   State formula structured to measure a locality’s ability to fund education.

        Long-term Goals  :  Identified expectations the organization has targeted to reach over a time period greater than
        three years.


        Maintenance:  The act of keeping capital assets in a state of good repair.  It includes preventative maintenance,
        normal periodic repairs, replacement of parts or structural components, and other activities needed to maintain
        the asset so that it continues to provide normal services and achieve its optimal life.


        Managed Competition:   A process that allows government to test the market for improved service delivery and
        pricing options by allowing both public and private entities to compete for a contract.


        Materials, Supplies and Repairs:  A budget category that includes expenditures for supplies, contracted services,
        and equipment maintenance.

        Modified accrual basis:  The basis of accounting under which transactions are recognized when they become both
        measurable (i.e., an amount can be determined) and available (i.e., able to liquidate liabilities of the current period)

        Net assets:  Total assets minus total liabilities of an individual or entity.


        Network Infrastructure:  In information technology and on the Internet, infrastructure is the physical hardware
        used to interconnect computers and users. Infrastructure includes the transmission media, including telephone
        lines, cable television lines, and satellites and antennas, and also the routers, aggregators, repeaters, and other
        devices that control transmission paths. Infrastructure also includes the software used to send, receive, and
        manage the signals that are transmitted.

        New Measure:   A performance measurement that the city has not captured or reported upon in previous years.


        NJDC (Norfolk Juvenile Detention Center):  A short-term, secured co-ed facility for court evolved youth.

               (
        NRHA Norfolk Redevelopment & Housing Authority):          The component unit that assists the city with
        conservation and redevelopment activities, property rehabilitation, management of public housing programs, and
        services and programs for low and moderate income families within Norfolk communities.


        Nuisance Abatement:    The reduction of objects that cause trouble, annoyance or inconvenience, such as
        abandoned or junk vehicles and trash.

        Objective:  Attached to a goal, it describes something to be accomplished in specific, well-defined and measurable
        terms and is achievable within a specific timeframe.


        Operating Budget:  An annual financial plan of operating expenditures of the General Fund, enterprise funds and
        internal service funds and the approved means of financing them.  The operating budget is the primary tool by

        570   Glossary

 = Page 10 =





            which most of the financing, acquisition, spending and service delivery activities of a government are planned and
            controlled.


            Operating Revenues and Expenditures:    Operating revenues and expenditures generally result from providing
            services and/or producing and delivering goods in connection with a fund’s principal ongoing operations.


            Ordinance:  A formal legislative enactment by the City Council, which has the full force and effect of law within the
            boundaries of the city.

            Outcome Measure:   The results of an activity, plan, process, or program and their comparison with the intended or
            projected results.

            Parking Facilities Fund:   A fund used to account for the operations of the city-owned parking facilities.


            Part-Time Position (Permanent):   A position regularly scheduled for no more than 30 hours per week.


            Personal Property Tax:   Taxes assessed each year by the Commissioner of Revenue's (COR) Office for all tangible
            personal property located within the City of Norfolk. A major set of tangible personal property for which taxes are
            collected is motor vehicles.

            Personnel Services:   Compensation for direct labor of persons in the employment of the city; salaries and wages
            paid to employees for full-time, part-time, and temporary work, including overtime, shift differential, and similar
            compensation.  The Personnel Services account group also includes fringe benefits paid for employees.

            Project Focus:   A targeted neighborhood revitalization program that provides an enhanced police patrol presence
            and increased code enforcement to address issues of crime and public safety in high crime neighborhoods.


            Proposed Budget:    The budget formally submitted by the City Manager to the City Council for its consideration.


            Proprietary Fund:   A fund that accounts for operations similar to those in the private sector.  This includes the
            enterprise funds and internal service funds.  The focus is on determination of net income, financial position and
            changes in financial position.


            Public Assistance:   Federal, state and local programs that provide a safety net (i.e. housing, medical assistance,
            money) for disadvantaged groups who lack the resources to provide basic necessities for themselves and their
            families.

            Public Amenities Fund:   Special revenue fund designated for tourism and visitor destination, improvements to
            existing cultural and entertainment facilities, and planning and preparation for new venues.  Revenues derived
            from one percentage point of the meals and hotel taxes.


            Public-Private Partnership:   A contractual agreement between the city and a private sector entity for the
            provision of public services or infrastructure.  Through this agreement, the skills and assets of each sector (public
            and private) are shared in delivering a service or facility for the use of the general public.  Rather than completely
            transferring public assets to the private sector, as with privatization, government and business work together to
            provide services with each party sharing in the risks and rewards potential in the delivery of the service and/or
            facility.

                                                                                                         Glossary   571

 = Page 11 =





        Purchased Services:   Services that are provided to an individual or group of individuals by an enterprise that is
        under contract with the city.


        Real Property Taxes:   Revenue derived from the tax assessed on residential, commercial or industrial property.


        Reserve:   An amount set aside in a fund balance to provide for expenditures from the unencumbered balances of
        continuing appropriations, economic uncertainties, and future apportionments, pending salary or price increase
        appropriations and appropriations for capital outlay projects.

        Resources:   Factors of production or service in terms of information, people, materials, capital, facilities, and
        equipment.

        Revenue:   The yield from various sources of income, such as taxes the city collects and receives into the treasury for
        public use.


        Revenue Anticipation Notes:    A short-term debt security issued on the premise that future revenues will be
        sufficient to meet repayment obligations.  These securities are repaid with future expected revenues from the
        completed project, which may come from sources like tolls or facility ticket sales.

        Revenue Bonds:    Limited liability obligations where revenues derived from the respective acquired or constructed
        assets are pledged to pay debt service.


        Rolling Stock:   The total number of vehicles and equipment in the city’s fleet (i.e. tractors, trailers, boats)

        Server:   A computer program that provides services to other computer programs in the same or other computers.


        Service:   The on-going sequence of specific tasks and activities that represent a continuous and distinct benefit
        provided to internal and external customers.


        Service Quality:  The manner or technique by which an activity was undertaken, and the achievement of a
        desirable end result (e.g., when filling a pothole there should be a service quality standard for how long that
        pothole should stay filled). Efficiency and effectiveness should be achieved within the context of a service quality
        standard.  Measuring any one of these without the other two can cause problems in terms of getting an accurate
        assessment of performance.


        Shared Expenses:   Revenue received from the state for its share of expenditures in activities that are considered to
        be a state/local responsibility.  Sources include the state's share of Commonwealth's Attorney, Sheriff,
        Commissioner of the Revenue, Treasurer, Medical Examiner, and Registrar/Electoral Board expenditures.


        Short-term Goals:   Identified expectations the organization has targeted to reach over a time period between one
        and three years.


        SNAP (Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program):    Provides financial assistance for food purchasing to low-
        and no-income people and families living in the U.S. It is a federal aid program, administered by the Food and
        Nutrition Service of the U.S. Department of Agriculture, but benefits are distributed by the individual U.S. states.





        572   Glossary

 = Page 12 =





            SOQ (Standards of Quality):  The statutory framework that establishes the minimal requirements for educational
            programs in the Virginia public schools.


            SOR Initiative (Staffing & Organization Redesign):   The effort to evaluate and appropriately allocate staff and
            positions throughout departments to improve productivity.


            Special Revenue Funds:    Funds used to account for the proceeds of specific financial resources (other than
            expendable trusts or major capital projects) requiring separate accounting because of legal or regulatory
            provisions or administrative action.  The individual Special Revenue funds are Cemeteries, Emergency
            Preparedness & Response, Golf Operations, Public Amenities, Storm Water Utility, and Towing & Recovery.


            SPSA (Southeastern Public Service Authority):    The organization that manages and operates solid waste
            transportation, processing and disposal programs and facilities for several cities within the Hampton Roads
            Region, to include Norfolk, Portsmouth, Virginia Beach, Chesapeake, Suffolk, Franklin, Isle of Wight and South
            Hampton County.

            Storehouse Fund:  A fund that is used by the Purchasing Office to acquire and issue operating departments (such
            as Public Works, Utilities) materials, parts and supplies that are used in the same form as purchased.



            Storm Water BMP(Best Management Practice):    Methods designed to control storm water runoff incorporating
            sediment control and soil stabilization.  Norfolk employs both structural (retention ponds) and nonstructural
            (education) methods of reducing the quantity and improving the quality of storm water runoff.


            Storm Water Fund:    A fund established to account for the operations of the city-owned environmental storm
            water management system  .

            Strategic Planning:   The continuous and systematic process whereby guiding members of the city make decisions
            about its future, develop the necessary procedures and operations to achieve the future, and determine how
            success will be measured.


            Strategic Priority:   Defined City Council guidance regarding broad service area goals.


            Surplus:   The excess of an entity's or fund’s assets over its liabilities (see also fund balance). The excess of revenues
            over expenditures or expenses during a single budget year.


            TANF (Temporary Assistance to Needy Families):   A block grant program to states that was designed to reform
            the nation's welfare system by moving recipients into work, promoting self-sufficiency and turning welfare into a
            program of temporary assistance.

            Tax Base:   All forms of wealth under the city’s jurisdiction that are taxable.


            Tax Increment Financing (TIF):   A public method used to finance infrastructure projects through future gains in
            tax revenue within a designated district that is established by a City Council ordinance.  These tax revenues are
            projected to grow as a result of the increase in the value of real estate within the designated district.






                                                                                                         Glossary   573

 = Page 13 =





        Technical Adjustment:   A routine budgetary action that occurs at the beginning of each budgetary cycle to adjust
        costs for such items as personnel (e.g. healthcare, retirement), contractual increase, prorated funding, and internal
        service fund charges.


        Tipping Fee:   The charge levied upon the quantity (calculated in tonnage) of waste received at a waste processing
        facility.


        TMDL (Total Maximum Daily Load):        A comprehensive pollution prevention initiative that has rigorous
        accountability measures (waste load allocations) to restore clean water in the Chesapeake Bay and its watershed.


        Transaction:    As pertains to the voter registrar, transaction is a measure of the number of computerized entries
        necessary to maintain voter registration and election records. Transaction totals vary depending on the number of
        elections and the quantity of voter initiated activity.

        Transfer:    An administrative means to move budgetary resources from one budget account to another.


        USDA (United States Department of Agriculture):   The Federal agency that leads the anti-hunger effort with the
        Food Stamp, School Lunch, School Breakfast, and the Women, Infants & Children (WIC) Programs.

        Vector Borne:   A disease or illness from an animal or insect that transmits a disease-producing organism from one
        host to another.



        Vector Control:   An effortto maintain order over animals and insects that transmit disease-producing organism
        from one to another.

        VDOT (Virginia Department of Transportation):    The state agency responsible for building, maintaining and
        operating the state's roads, bridges and tunnels.


        Vision:   An objective statement that describes an entity’s most desirable future state.  An organizational vision
        employs the skills, knowledge, innovation and foresight of management and the workforce in order to
        communicate effectively the desired future state.

        VML (Virginia Municipal League):   A statewide, nonprofit, nonpartisan association of city, town and county
        governments established to improve and assist local governments through legislative advocacy, research,
        education and other services.



        VPDES(Virginia Pollution Discharge & Elimination System):   A permit from the state to discharge storm water
        to natural bodies of water since, unlike sewage, storm water is not treated.

        Wastewater Utility Fund:   A fund established to account for the operations of the city-owned wastewater system.


        Water Utility Fund:   A fund established to account for operations of the city-owned water system.

        Working Capital:   Current assets minus current liabilities.  Working capital measures how much in liquid assets an
        entity has available to build its business or activity.





        574   Glossary

 = Page 14 =




            A                                                     Emergency Preparedness And Response . . . . . . .387
                                                                  Enterprise Fund Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .395
            Acknowledgements. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .3  Enterprise Funds
            Appropriations. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 45  Parking Facilities Fund . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .408
                                                                     Wastewater. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .405
            B                                                        Water . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .397
                                                                  Estimated Expenditures by Fund Type. . . . . . . . . . .30
            Basis of Budgeting and Accounting. . . . . . . . . . . . . 19
            Budget Calendar. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22  Estimated Expenditures by Use (All Funds). . . . . . .28
            Budget Overview . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .1  Estimated General Fund Expenditures by Area. . .32
            Budget Process . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 20  Estimated General Fund Revenues by Source. . . .24
                                                                  Estimated Revenues by Source (All Funds). . . . . . .26
                                                                  Executive
            C                                                        City Manager. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .119

            Capital Improvement Plan. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 427  Communications and Public Information. . .128
            Cemeteries . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 379  Office of Budget and Grants Management. .124
            Central Appropriations. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 237  Office to End Homelessness. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .130
            Child Nutrition Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 360
            Circuit Court Judges. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 162  F
            City Attorney . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 137
            City Auditor. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 113  Finance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .201
            City Clerk . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 105  Financial Policies . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .12
            City Council. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 103  Fire-Rescue. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .319
            City Indebtedness. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 54  Fleet Management . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .421
            City Manager . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 119  Fund Structure . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .16
            City of Norfolk Government . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .5
            City Real Estate Assessor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 109  G
            City Treasurer . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 148  General District Court. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .158
            Clerk of the Circuit Court . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 155  General Fund Balance Reserves . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .50
            Commissioner of the Revenue. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 143  General Fund Budget Overview . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .23
            Commonwealth's Attorney. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 169  General Fund Expenditure Summary . . . . . . . . . . . .71
            Communications and Public Information . . . . . . 128  General Fund Expenditures . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .69
            Communications and Technology . . . . . . . . . . . . . 189  General Fund Revenue Summary. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .61
            Community Development                                 General Fund Revenues. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .59
                Development . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 230  General Management
                Planning and Community Development . . . 223         Communications and Technology. . . . . . . . . .189
            Constitutional Officers                                  Finance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .201
                City Treasurer . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 148  General Services. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .207
                Commissioner of the Revenue. . . . . . . . . . . . . 143  Human Resources . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .215
            Cultural Facilities, Arts and Entertainment. . . . . . 263  General Services. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .207
                                                                                                            ,
                                                                  Glossary. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .561 563
            D                                                     Golf Operations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .384
            Debt Service. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 343
                Debt Service . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 343  H
            Department of Law                                     Healthcare Fund. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .417
                City Attorney. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 137  Human Resources . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .215
            Development. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 230  Human Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .299

            E                                                     I

            Education Funds . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 345  Internal Service Fund Summary . . . . . . . . . . .413 415
                                                                                                            ,
            Elections. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 183  Internal Service Funds
                Elections. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 183  Fleet Management . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .421


                                                                                                                   575

 = Page 15 =




            Healthcare Fund . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .417  Performance Measures . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .350
            Storehouse. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .419  Personnel Staffing Summary. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .52
                                                              Planning and Community Development . . . . . . .223
        J                                                     Police . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .311
                                                              Priority. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .93
        Judicial                                              Priority Setting Process Narrative. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .95
            Circuit Court Judges. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .162  Public Amenities . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .385
            Clerk of the Circuit Court . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .155  Public Health. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .293
            Commonwealth's Attorney . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .169  Public Health and Assistance
            General District Court . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .158  Human Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .299
            Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court. . . . .160     Public Health. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .293
            Magistrate . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .167  Public Safety
            Norfolk Juvenile Court Service Unit . . . . . . . .164  Fire-Rescue. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .319
            Sheriff and Jail . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .175  Police . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .311
        Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court. . . . . . . . .160  Public Works . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .329
                                                                  Public Works . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .329
        L
                                                              R
        Legislative
            City Auditor. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .113  Reader's Guide to the Budget . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .10
            City Clerk . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .105  Recreation, Parks and Open Space . . . . . . . . . . . . .281
            City Council. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .103
            City Real Estate Assessor. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .109  S
        Libraries . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .257
                                                              School Grants . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .358
        M                                                     School Operating Fund . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .356
                                                              Sheriff and Jail. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .175
        Magistrate . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .167  Special Revenue Fund Summary . . . . . . . . . .361 363
                                                                                                         ,
        Major Revenue Sources. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 34  Special Revenue Funds
                                                   ,
        Miscellaneous Statistical Information . . . . . 547 549   Cemeteries. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .379
                                                                  Emergency Preparedness And Response . . .387
        N                                                         Golf Operations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .384
                                                                  Norfolk Community Services Board . . . . . . . .365
        Non Departmental Appropriations. . . . . . . . . . . . .235  Public Amenities . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .385
        Norfolk Community Services Board . . . . . . . . . . . .365  Storm Water Management. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .371
        Norfolk Juvenile Court Service Unit . . . . . . . . . . . .164  Tax Increment Financing. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .392
        Norfolk Public Schools. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .347  Towing and Recovery Operations . . . . . . . . . .376
        Norfolk Public Schools Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . .354
                                                              Storehouse. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .419
                                                              Storm Water Management. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .371
        O

        Office of Budget and Grants Management . . . . .124   T
        Office to End Homelessness . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .130  Tax Increment Financing. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .392
        Outside Agencies . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .243
                                                              Tax Rates and Fees. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .48
                                                              The National Maritime Center. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .276
        P                                                     Towing and Recovery Operations . . . . . . . . . . . . . .376
        Parking Facilities Fund. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .408  Transfers From/To . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .51
        Parks, Recreation and Culture
            Cultural Facilities, Arts and Entertainment. .263  W
            Libraries . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .257  Wastewater . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .405
            Recreation, Parks and Open Space . . . . . . . . .281  Water . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .397
            The National Maritime Center. . . . . . . . . . . . . .276
            Zoological Park. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .270


        576

 = Page 16 =




            Y

            Yearly Maturity of Long-Term Debt. . . . . . . . . . . . . . 57

            Z

            Zoological Park . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 270













































































                                                                                                                   577

 = Page 17 =
