



       Getting Help

       n  The American Red Cross can help you by
          p roviding you with a voucher to purchase            After
          n ew clothing, groceries, essential medications,
          bedding, essential furnishings, and other items
          to meet emergency needs.  Listen to local            a Flood:
          radio stations to find out where to go for this
          assistance, or look up American Red Cross in
          the phone book and call.

       n  The Red Cross can provide you with a                 The
          cleanup kit: mop, broom, bucket, and
          cleaning supplies.
       n  Contact your insurance agent to discuss              First
          c l a i m s .
       n  Listen to your radio for information on
          assistance that may be provided by the
          state or federal government and other                Steps
          o r g a n i z a t i o n s .

       n  If you hire cleanup or repair contractors,
          be sure they are qualified to do the job.
          Be wary of people who drive through
          neighborhoods offering help in cleaning up
          or repairing your home.  Check re f e re n c e s .








       Issued in furtherance of the In t e rnational Decade
               for Natural Disaster Re d u c t i o n .
















                                              ARC 4476
                                            FEMA L-198
                                              Aug. 1992

 = Page 1 =




       Your home has been flooded.  Although                     Staying Healthy
       floodwaters may be down in some areas,
       many dangers still exist.  He re are things to            n  A flood can cause emotional and physical
       remember in the days ahead.                                 s t ress.  You need to look after yourself and
                                                                   your family as you focus on cleanup and
       n  Roads may be closed because they have been               re p a i r.
          damaged or are cove red by water. Ba r r i c a d e s     • Rest often and eat we l l .
          h a ve been placed for your protection.  If yo u
          come upon a barricade or a flooded road, go              • Keep a manageable schedule.  Make a list
          another way.                                                and do jobs one at a time.
       n  Keep listening to the radio for news about               • Discuss your concerns with others and
                                                                      seek help.  Contract the Red Cross for
          what to do, where to go, or places to avo i d .             information on emotional support
       n  Emergency workers will be assisting people in               a vailable in your area.
          flooded areas.  You can help them by staying
          off the roads and out of the way.                      Cleaning Up and Repairing

       n  If you  m u s t  walk or drive in areas that have      Your Home
          been flooded —
         • Stay on firm ground.  Moving water only               n  Turn off the electricity at the main breaker
            6 inches deep can sweep you off your  feet.            of fuse box, even if the power is off in yo u r
            Standing water may be electrically charged             c o m m u n i t y. That way,  yo u  can decide when
            f rom underground or downed power lines.               your home is dry enough to turn it back on.
         • Flooding may have caused familiar places to           n  Get a copy of the book  Repairing Your Fl o o d e d
            change.  Floodwaters often erode roads and             Ho m e . It will tell yo u :
            walkways.  Flood debris may hide animals               • How to enter your home safely.
            and broken bottles, and it ís also ve ry slip-         • How to protect your home and belongings
            p e ry.  Avoid walking or driving thro u g h              f rom further damage.
            f l o o d w a t e r s .
       n  Play it safe.  Additional flooding or flash              • How to re c o rd damage to support
                                                                      insurance claims and requests for assistance.
          floods can occur.  Listen for local warnings
          and information.  If your car stalls in rapidly          • How to check for gas or water leaks
          rising waters, get out immediately and climb                and how to have service re s t o re d .
          to higher gro u n d .                                    • How to clean up appliances, furniture ,
                                                                      floors, and other belongings.
                                                                      Repairing Your Flooded Ho m e  is ava i l a b l e
                                                                   f ree from the American Red Cross or yo u r
                                                                   state or local emergency manager.

 = Page 2 =
