<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20130516</CreaDate><CreaTime>14405000</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><ArcGISstyle>FGDC CSDGM Metadata</ArcGISstyle><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><itemProps><itemName Sync="TRUE">PortVAzone</itemName><nativeExtBox><westBL Sync="TRUE">-98940.268900</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">325205.923200</eastBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">60441.245600</southBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">385297.680400</northBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></nativeExtBox><itemSize Sync="TRUE">2.212</itemSize><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\Winkeltripel\Data\state\VEDP\regions\PortVA_EconomicInfrastructureDevelopmentZone\PortVAzone.shp</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation><imsContentType Sync="TRUE" export="False">002</imsContentType></itemProps><coordRef><type Sync="TRUE">Projected</type><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><csUnits Sync="TRUE">Linear Unit: Meter (1.000000)</csUnits><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_Virginia_Lambert</projcsn><peXml Sync="TRUE">&lt;ProjectedCoordinateSystem xsi:type='typens:ProjectedCoordinateSystem' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema' xmlns:typens='http://www.esri.com/schemas/ArcGIS/10.1'&gt;&lt;WKT&gt;PROJCS[&amp;quot;NAD_1983_Virginia_Lambert&amp;quot;,GEOGCS[&amp;quot;GCS_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,DATUM[&amp;quot;D_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,SPHEROID[&amp;quot;GRS_1980&amp;quot;,6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&amp;quot;Greenwich&amp;quot;,0.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Degree&amp;quot;,0.0174532925199433]],PROJECTION[&amp;quot;Lambert_Conformal_Conic&amp;quot;],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;False_Easting&amp;quot;,0.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;False_Northing&amp;quot;,0.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Central_Meridian&amp;quot;,-79.5],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Standard_Parallel_1&amp;quot;,37.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Standard_Parallel_2&amp;quot;,39.5],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Latitude_Of_Origin&amp;quot;,36.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Meter&amp;quot;,1.0],AUTHORITY[&amp;quot;EPSG&amp;quot;,3968]]&lt;/WKT&gt;&lt;XOrigin&gt;-37232800&lt;/XOrigin&gt;&lt;YOrigin&gt;-28884600&lt;/YOrigin&gt;&lt;XYScale&gt;120957855.10008635&lt;/XYScale&gt;&lt;ZOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/ZOrigin&gt;&lt;ZScale&gt;10000&lt;/ZScale&gt;&lt;MOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/MOrigin&gt;&lt;MScale&gt;10000&lt;/MScale&gt;&lt;XYTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/XYTolerance&gt;&lt;ZTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/ZTolerance&gt;&lt;MTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/MTolerance&gt;&lt;HighPrecision&gt;true&lt;/HighPrecision&gt;&lt;WKID&gt;3968&lt;/WKID&gt;&lt;LatestWKID&gt;3968&lt;/LatestWKID&gt;&lt;/ProjectedCoordinateSystem&gt;</peXml></coordRef></DataProperties><SyncDate>20130516</SyncDate><SyncTime>15061100</SyncTime><ModDate>20130516</ModDate><ModTime>15061100</ModTime><scaleRange><minScale>150000000</minScale><maxScale>5000</maxScale></scaleRange><ArcGISProfile>FGDC</ArcGISProfile></Esri><mdLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"/></mdLang><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20130516</mdDateSt><mdStanName>ArcGIS Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>1.0</mdStanVer><distInfo xmlns=""><distTranOps xmlns=""><onLineSrc xmlns=""><linkage>http://gis.vedp.org/data_resources.aspx</linkage></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">2.212</transSize></distTranOps><distFormat xmlns=""><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName><formatVer>Esri ArcGIS 10.1</formatVer></distFormat></distInfo><dataIdInfo><idCitation xmlns=""><resTitle Sync="FALSE">Port of Virginia Economic &amp; Infrastructure Development Zone</resTitle><date><pubDate>2012-07-02T00:00:00</pubDate><reviseDate>2013-05-16T00:00:00</reviseDate></date><presForm xmlns=""><PresFormCd value="005"/></presForm><presForm xmlns=""><fgdcGeoform>vector digital data</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citRespParty xmlns=""><rpOrgName>Virginia Economic Development Partnership</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role><rpCntInfo xmlns=""><cntAddress addressType="both"><delPoint>901 East Byrd Street, 18th Fl. West</delPoint><city>Richmond</city><adminArea>Virginia</adminArea><postCode>23218-0798</postCode><country>US</country><delPoint>P.O. Box 798</delPoint></cntAddress><cntPhone><voiceNum tddtty="">804-545-5600</voiceNum></cntPhone></rpCntInfo></citRespParty></idCitation><idPurp>The purpose of this dataset is to show communities designated by the Virginia General Assembly to be a part of the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone. These communities are elligible to receive monies from the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone Grant Fund.</idPurp><idCredit>Virginia Economic Development Partnership</idCredit><idStatus><ProgCd value="001"/></idStatus><resMaint xmlns=""><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="009"/></maintFreq></resMaint><placeKeys xmlns=""><keyword>Virginia</keyword><keyword>Commonwealth</keyword><keyword>the Counties of Brunswick</keyword><keyword>Chesterfield</keyword><keyword>Charles City</keyword><keyword>Clarke</keyword><keyword>Dinwiddie</keyword><keyword>Frederick</keyword><keyword>Gloucester</keyword><keyword>Greensville</keyword><keyword>Henrico</keyword><keyword>Hanover</keyword><keyword>Isle of Wight</keyword><keyword>James City</keyword><keyword>Mecklenburg</keyword><keyword>Montgomery</keyword><keyword>New Kent</keyword><keyword>Page</keyword><keyword>Prince George</keyword><keyword>Shenandoah</keyword><keyword>Southampton</keyword><keyword>Surry</keyword><keyword>Sussex</keyword><keyword>Warren</keyword><keyword>and York; and the Cities of Chesapeake</keyword><keyword>Colonial Heights</keyword><keyword>Emporia</keyword><keyword>Franklin</keyword><keyword>Hampton</keyword><keyword>Hopewell</keyword><keyword>Newport News</keyword><keyword>Norfolk</keyword><keyword>Petersburg</keyword><keyword>Poquoson</keyword><keyword>Portsmouth</keyword><keyword>Richmond</keyword><keyword>Suffolk</keyword><keyword>Virginia Beach</keyword><keyword>Williamsburg</keyword><keyword>and Winchester.</keyword></placeKeys><themeKeys xmlns=""><thesaName><resTitle>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</resTitle></thesaName><keyword>economy</keyword></themeKeys><searchKeys><keyword>economy</keyword><keyword>Virginia</keyword><keyword>Commonwealth</keyword><keyword>the Counties of Brunswick</keyword><keyword>Chesterfield</keyword><keyword>Charles City</keyword><keyword>Clarke</keyword><keyword>Dinwiddie</keyword><keyword>Frederick</keyword><keyword>Gloucester</keyword><keyword>Greensville</keyword><keyword>Henrico</keyword><keyword>Hanover</keyword><keyword>Isle of Wight</keyword><keyword>James City</keyword><keyword>Mecklenburg</keyword><keyword>Montgomery</keyword><keyword>New Kent</keyword><keyword>Page</keyword><keyword>Prince George</keyword><keyword>Shenandoah</keyword><keyword>Southampton</keyword><keyword>Surry</keyword><keyword>Sussex</keyword><keyword>Warren</keyword><keyword>and York; and the Cities of Chesapeake</keyword><keyword>Colonial Heights</keyword><keyword>Emporia</keyword><keyword>Franklin</keyword><keyword>Hampton</keyword><keyword>Hopewell</keyword><keyword>Newport News</keyword><keyword>Norfolk</keyword><keyword>Petersburg</keyword><keyword>Poquoson</keyword><keyword>Portsmouth</keyword><keyword>Richmond</keyword><keyword>Suffolk</keyword><keyword>Virginia Beach</keyword><keyword>Williamsburg</keyword><keyword>and Winchester.</keyword></searchKeys><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="001"/></spatRpType><dataLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"/></dataLang><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.1.1.3143</envirDesc><dataExt xmlns=""><geoEle xmlns=""><GeoBndBox><westBL>-80.649777</westBL><eastBL>-75.722725</eastBL><southBL>36.487042</southBL><northBL>39.471579</northBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Period xmlns=""><tmBegin>2013-05-16T00:00:00</tmBegin></TM_Period></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></dataExt><idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;§ 62.1-132.3:2. Grants to companies locating or expanding in the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone; grant fund established.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;A. From such funds as may be appropriated by the General Assembly and any gifts, grants, or donations from public or private sources, and any funds transferred at the request of the Executive Director from the Port Opportunity Fund created pursuant to § 62.1-132.3:1, there is hereby created in the state treasury a special nonreverting, permanent fund to be known as the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone Grant Fund (the Fund), to be administered by the Virginia Port Authority. The Fund shall be established on the books of the Comptroller. Any moneys remaining in the Fund at the end of each fiscal year, including interest thereon, shall not revert to the general fund but shall remain in the Fund. Expenditures and disbursements from the Fund, which shall be in the form of grants, shall be made by the State Treasurer on warrants issued by the Comptroller upon written request signed by the Executive Director. Moneys in the Fund shall be used solely for the purpose of grants to qualified applicants to the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone Grant Program.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;B. The Virginia General Assembly does hereby designate the following localities to be part of the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone: the Counties of Brunswick, Chesterfield, Charles City, Clarke, Dinwiddie, Frederick, Gloucester, Greensville, Henrico, Hanover, Isle of Wight, James City, Mecklenburg, Montgomery, New Kent, Page, Prince George, Shenandoah, Southampton, Surry, Sussex, Warren, and York; and the Cities of Chesapeake, Colonial Heights, Emporia, Franklin, Hampton, Hopewell, Newport News, Norfolk, Petersburg, Poquoson, Portsmouth, Richmond, Suffolk, Virginia Beach, Williamsburg, and Winchester.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;C. As used in this section, unless the context requires a different meaning:&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;"New, permanent full-time position" means a job of an indefinite duration, created by a qualified company as a result of operations within the Zone, requiring a minimum of 35 hours of an employee's time per week for the entire normal year of the company's operations, which normal year shall consist of at least 48 weeks, or a position of indefinite duration that requires a minimum of 35 hours of an employee's time per week for the portion of the taxable year in which the employee was initially hired for the qualified company's location within the Zone. Seasonal or temporary positions, or jobs created when a position is shifted from an existing location in the Commonwealth to the qualified company's location within the Zone, and positions in building and grounds maintenance, security, and other positions that are ancillary to the principal activities performed by the employees at the qualified company's location within the Zone shall not qualify as new, permanent full-time positions.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;"Qualified company" means a corporation, limited liability company, partnership, joint, venture, or other business entity that (i) locates or expands a facility within the Zone; (ii) creates at least 25 new, permanent full-time positions for qualified full-time employees at a facility within the Zone during its first year of operation within the Zone or during the year when the expansion occurs; (iii) is involved in maritime commerce or exports or imports manufactured goods through the Port of Virginia; and (iv) is engaged in one or more of the following: the distribution, freight forwarding, freight handling, goods processing, manufacturing, warehousing, crossdocking, transloading, or wholesaling of goods exported and imported through the Port of Virginia; ship building and ship repair; dredging; marine construction; or offshore energy exploration or extraction.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;"Qualified full-time employee" means an employee filling a new, permanent full-time position in the qualified company's location within the Zone. A "qualified full-time employee" does not include an employee (i) for whom a tax credit was previously earned pursuant to §§ § 58.1-439 or 58.1-439.12:06 by a related party as defined in § 267(b) of the Internal Revenue Code or by a trade or business under common control as defined in § 52(b) of the Internal Revenue Code; (ii) who was previously employed in the same job function at an existing location in Virginia by a related party as defined in § 267(b) of the Internal Revenue Code; or (iii) whose job function was previously performed at a different location in Virginia by an employee of a related party as defined in § 267(b) of the Internal Revenue Code or a trade or business under common control as defined in § 52(b) of the Internal Revenue Code.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;"Zone" means the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;D. Beginning January 1, 2013, but not later than June 30, 2020, and subject to appropriation, any qualified company that locates or expands a facility within the Port of Virginia Economic and Infrastructure Development Zone shall be eligible to apply for a one-time grant from the Fund, in an amount determined as follows:&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;1. One thousand dollars per new, permanent full-time position if the qualified company creates at least 25 new, permanent full-time positions for qualified full-time employees during its first year of operation within the Zone or during the year in which the expansion occurs;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;2. Fifteen hundred dollars per new, permanent full-time position if the qualified company creates at least 50 new, permanent full-time positions for qualified full-time employees during its first year of operation within the Zone or during the year in which the expansion occurs;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;3. Two thousand dollars per new, permanent full-time position if the qualified company creates at least 75 new, permanent full-time positions for qualified full-time employees during its first year of operation within the Zone or during the year in which the expansion occurs; and&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;4. Three thousand dollars per new, permanent full-time position if the qualified company creates at least 100 new, permanent full-time positions for qualified full-time employees during its first year of operation within the Zone or during the year in which the expansion occurs.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;E. The maximum amount of grant allowable per qualified company in any given fiscal year is $500,000. The maximum amount of grants allowable among all qualified companies in any given fiscal year is $5,000,000.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;F. To qualify for a grant pursuant to this section, a qualified company must apply for the grant not later than March 31 in the year immediately following the location or expansion of a facility within the Zone pursuant to an application process developed by the Virginia Port Authority. Within 90 days after the filing deadline, the Executive Director shall certify to the Comptroller and the qualified company the amount of grant to which the qualified company is entitled under this section. Payment of each grant shall be made by check issued by the Treasurer of Virginia on warrant of the Comptroller within 60 days of such certification and in the order that each completed eligible application is received. In the event that the amount of eligible grants requested in a fiscal year exceeds the funds available in the Fund or $5,000,000, such grants shall be paid in the next fiscal year in which funds are available.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;G. Prior to receipt of a grant, the qualified company shall enter into a memorandum of understanding with the Virginia Port Authority establishing the requirements for maintaining the number of new, permanent full-time positions for qualified employees at the qualified company's location within the Zone. If the number of new, permanent full-time positions for any of the three years immediately following receipt of a grant falls below the number of new, permanent full-time positions created during the year for which the grant is claimed, the amount of the grant must be recalculated using the decreased number of new, permanent full-time positions and the qualified company shall repay the difference.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;H. No qualified company shall apply for a grant nor shall one be awarded under this section to an otherwise qualified company if (i) a credit pursuant to §§ § 58.1-439 or 58.1-439.12:06 is claimed for the same employees or for capital expenditures at the same facility by the qualified company, by a related party as defined in § 267(b) of the Internal Revenue Code, or by a trade or business under common control as defined in § 52(b) of the Internal Revenue Code or (ii) the qualified company was a party to a reorganization as defined in § 368(b) of the Internal Revenue Code, and any corporation involved in the reorganization as defined in § 368(a) of the Internal Revenue Code previously received a grant under this section for the same facility or operations.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;I. The Virginia Port Authority, with the assistance of the Virginia Economic Development Partnership, shall develop guidelines establishing procedures and requirements for qualifying for the grant, including the affirmative determination that each applicant is a qualified company, as defined above, engaged in a port-related business. The guidelines shall be exempt from the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.).&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;2. That the provisions of this act shall not become effective unless an appropriation of general funds effectuating the purposes of this act is included in a general appropriation act passed by the 2013 Session of the General Assembly, which becomes law.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;3. That the General Assembly determines that the requirements of the second enactment of this act have been met.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs><dataChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></dataChar><idPoC xmlns=""><rpOrgName>Virginia Economic Development Partnership</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role><rpCntInfo xmlns=""><cntAddress addressType="both"><delPoint>901 East Byrd Street, 18th Fl. West</delPoint><city>Richmond</city><adminArea>Virginia</adminArea><postCode>23218-0798</postCode><country>US</country><delPoint>P.O. Box 798</delPoint></cntAddress><cntPhone><voiceNum tddtty="">804-545-5600</voiceNum></cntPhone></rpCntInfo><displayName>Virginia Economic Development Partnership</displayName></idPoC><resConst><LegConsts xmlns=""><useLimit>Pursuant to Section 54.1-402, paragraph C of the Code of Virginia, which is quoted below, this data may not be used for purposes listed in said paragraph C, since the data was not created, nor is it maintained under the supervision of a licensed land surveyor. "C. Persons utilizing photogrammetric methods or similar remote sensing technology shall not be required to be licensed as a land surveyor pursuant to subsection B of § 54.1-404 or 54.1-406 to: (i) determine topography or contours, or to depict physical improvements, provided such maps or other documents shall not be used for the design, modification, or construction of improvements to real property or for flood plain determination, or (ii) graphically show existing property lines and boundaries on maps or other documents provided such depicted property lines and boundaries shall only be used for general information. Any determination of topography or contours, or depiction of physical improvements, utilizing photogrammetric methods or similar remote sensing technology by persons not licensed as a land surveyor pursuant to § 54.1-406 shall not show any property monumentation or property metes and bounds, nor provide any measurement showing the relationship of any physical improvements to any property line or boundary. Any person not licensed pursuant to subsection B of § 54.1-404 or 54.1-406 preparing documentation pursuant to subsection C of § 54.1-402 shall note the following on such documentation: 'Any determination of topography or contours, or any depiction of physical improvements, property lines or boundaries is for general information only and shall not be used for the design, modification, or construction of improvements to real property or for flood plain determination."
</useLimit></LegConsts></resConst><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="005"/></tpCat><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode><westBL Sync="TRUE">-80.649774</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-75.722724</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">39.471571</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">36.487035</southBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><dqInfo xmlns=""><dqScope><scpLvl><ScopeCd value="005"/></scpLvl></dqScope><dataLineage><dataSource xmlns="" type=""><srcDesc>Esri locality boundaries for Virginia</srcDesc><srcMedName><MedNameCd value="001"/></srcMedName><srcCitatn xmlns=""><resTitle>Esri ArcGIS 10 Data</resTitle><resAltTitle>Esri ArcGIS 10 Data</resAltTitle></srcCitatn></dataSource></dataLineage></dqInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><geometObjs Name="PortVAzone"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd value="002" Sync="TRUE"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">39</geoObjCnt></geometObjs><topLvl><TopoLevCd value="001" Sync="TRUE"></TopoLevCd></topLvl></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed Name="PortVAzone" xmlns=""><enttyp><enttypl Sync="TRUE">PortVAzone</enttypl><enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">39</enttypc></enttyp><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>FIPS</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">FIPS</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">5</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef>Federal Information Processing Standard Number</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>FIPS_State</attrlabl><attalias Sync="FALSE">FIPS State</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">2</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef>Federal Information Processing Standard State Number</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>FIPS_Count</attrlabl><attalias Sync="FALSE">FIPS County</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">3</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef>Federal Information Processing Standard County Number</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>Name</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Name</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">254</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef>Locality Name</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>Shape_area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape_area</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr xmlns=""><attrlabl>Shape_len</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape_len</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr></detailed></eainfo><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode code="3968" Sync="TRUE"/><idCodeSpace Sync="TRUE">EPSG</idCodeSpace><idVersion Sync="TRUE">7.11.2</idVersion></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spdoinfo><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="PortVAzone"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom code="4" Sync="TRUE"></efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">39</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">TRUE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><mdContact xmlns=""><rpOrgName>Virginia Economic Development Partnership</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role><rpCntInfo><cntAddress addressType="both"><delPoint>901 East Byrd Street, 18th Fl. West</delPoint><city>Richmond</city><adminArea>Virginia</adminArea><postCode>23218-0798</postCode><country>US</country><delPoint>P.O. Box 798</delPoint></cntAddress><cntPhone><voiceNum tddtty="">804-545-5600</voiceNum></cntPhone></rpCntInfo><displayName>Virginia Economic Development Partnership</displayName></mdContact><mdMaint xmlns=""><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="009"/></maintFreq></mdMaint></metadata>
