

                 
                 Board of Supervisors                                            General Operating Fund



               KEY WORKPLAN ITEMS

               1. Serve as policy making board, and, within the framework of the Constitution and Code of Virginia,

                   approve and enforce County's comprehensive plan and land use, set local tax rate, adopt annual
                   operating and capital budgets, approve ordinances, and make appointments to various boards and
                   commissions
               2. Record and maintain official documents for Board of Supervisors and James City Service Authority

                   Board of Directors, such as meeting minutes and related documents and other Boards and
                   Commissions such as appointment lists, files and correspondence

               3. Prepare and distribute Board of Supervisors and James City Service Authority Board of Directors
                   agenda packets and materials

               4. Notify the public about hearings and meetings as required by Code

               5. Support Board of Supervisors and James City Service Authority Board of Directors by responding to
                   or directing phone and mail inquiries to the appropriate person
               6. Represent citizens from each of the County’s five election districts: Berkeley, Jamestown, Powhatan,

                   Roberts and Stonehouse
               7. Hold regularly scheduled public meetings and work sessions and serve on other local and regional

                   boards and commissions

               BUDGET SUMMARY
                                                     FY 12             FY 13              FY 14
                                                    Adopted           Adopted              Plan

                                  Personnel    $     117,476     $       113,934     $     117,342
                                  Operating           77,900              82,900            82,900
                                      Total    $     195,376     $       196,834     $     200,242


               PERSONNEL

                          Full-time Personnel              1                   1                 1

               PERFORMANCE MEASURES
                                                            FY 11        FY 12        FY 13         FY 14
                                                            Actual      Projected    Adopted         Plan

                      # Appointments made to boards and
                                          commissions           40            33           30            30
                                      # Public Hearings         79          New            80            80


               BUDGET COMMENTS

               This budget reflects a continuation of the current level of service.  Recognition expenses are consolidated
               from other divisions into this budget.









                                                           Page C-3


 = Page 1 =
